<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE texts SYSTEM "additional_text.dtd">
<texts xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="additional_text.xsd">
	<text id="intro">
		<croatian>
			<p>Na drugom medunarodnom kongresu podzemne topografije (odrzanom u Breitenbachu, Svicarska, 1995.) na dnevnom redu nasli su se speleoloski simboli pojedinih zemalja. Najznacajniji simboli bili su prihvaceni na novi zajednicki popis, te objavljeni kao prijedlog medunarodnog popisa speleoloskih simbola. Ovaj prijedlog bio je predmet rasprave i na UIS kongresu u La Chaux de Fonds, te tamo i izglasan od strane delegata svih zemalja.</p>
			<p>Popis simbola bi trebao biti opsezna medunarodna osnova, na koju svaka zemlja moze, prema potrebi, dodati vlastite simbole. Stoga nije zabranjeno rabiti dodatne smislene simbole.</p>
			<p>Raspravom medu aktivnim mjernicima i crtacima doslo se do zakljucka da je nacrt sa svim svojim simbolima i napomenama tek polovica zadovoljavajuce dokumentacije o speleoloskom objektu. Drugi, takoder vrlo vazni dio dokumentacije je opsezan opis objekta, ukljucujuci i fenomene koji se ne mogu skicirati na nacrtu. Napisan opis je stoga vrlo vazan faktor pri dokumentiranju speleoloskog objekta. Opazanja o geoloskoj strukturi , sedimentima, klimatskim uvjetima, hidrologiji, kao i o flori i fauni, opis lokacije i puta do ulaza, kratki sazetak o povjesti istrazivanja, kao i popis potrebne opreme tocke su opsezne dokumentacije speloloskog objekta. Pretpostavke o mogucnosti nastavka galerija, te teorije o nastanku pojedinih kanala zaokruzuju opis speleoloskog objekta i zajedno sa dobrim nacrtom tvore vrijednu osnovu za daljnji rad.</p>
			<p>Stoga se preporuca ne samo crtanje nacrta (tlocrta i ispruzenog profila) speleoloskog objekta, vec i opisivanje objekta rjecima.</p>
		</croatian>
		<dutch>
			<p>At the "Second International Meeting on subterrainean Topography" in Breitenbach (Switzerland), 1995, Cave Signature lists of different countries had been the subject of discusssion. The essential symbols had been integrated into a new list and published as a proposal of an international cave signature list. This proposal has been debated thoroughly at the UIS congress in La Chaux de Fonds and then voted and accepted by the national delegates of each country.</p>
			<p>This list should be a comprehensive, international foundation, on which each country can, if necessary, introduce their own additional symbols. It is therefore not forbidden to use additional meaningful symbols.</p>
			<p>Among active surveyors and draftsmen it turned out, that the plan with all its symbols and signatures is only "half" of the work, documenting a cave-system. The other, also very important part is a comprehensive description of the system, including phenomena that can't be sketched in a map. The written cave-description therefore is a very important factor in documenting the cave. Observing geology, sediments, climatic conditions, hydrology as well as watching fauna and flora, describing the location and path to the cave entrance, an abstract on the history of exploration, last not least lists on needed equipment, all those points belong to a comprehensive cave documentaion.</p>
			<p>Assumptions on continuations of galleries just as theories on the genesis of a certain passage round up the cave description and form together with a welldone cave map a valuable foundation for further work.</p>
			<p>It is therefore recommended, not only to sketch a cave plan and a developed section (see documentation on the 9th National Congress 1991, Charmey), but also the cave description mentioned above!</p>
		</dutch>
		<english>
			<p>At the "Second International Meeting on subterrainean Topography" in Breitenbach (Switzerland), 1995, Cave Signature lists of different countries had been the subject of discusssion. The essential symbols had been integrated into a new list and published as a proposal of an international cave signature list. This proposal has been debated thoroughly at the UIS congress in La Chaux de Fonds and then voted and accepted by the national delegates of each country.</p>
			<p>This list should be a comprehensive, international foundation, on which each country can, if necessary, introduce their own additional symbols. It is therefore not forbidden to use additional meaningful symbols.</p>
			<p>Among active surveyors and draftsmen it turned out, that the plan with all its symbols and signatures is only "half" of the work, documenting a cave-system. The other, also very important part is a comprehensive description of the system, including phenomena that can't be sketched in a map. The written cave-description therefore is a very important factor in documenting the cave. Observing geology, sediments, climatic conditions, hydrology as well as watching fauna and flora, describing the location and path to the cave entrance, an abstract on the history of exploration, last not least lists on needed equipment, all those points belong to a comprehensive cave documentaion.</p>
			<p>Assumptions on continuations of galleries just as theories on the genesis of a certain passage round up the cave description and form together with a welldone cave map a valuable foundation for further work.</p>
			<p>It is therefore recommended, not only to sketch a cave plan and a developed section (see documentation on the 9th National Congress 1991, Charmey), but also the cave description mentioned above!</p>
		</english>
		<french>
			<p>A la deuxième réunion internationale de topographie à Breitenbach (Suisse), en 1995, les différentes listes de symboles utilisés en topographie ont été discutées. Les symboles importants ont été reportés dans une nouvelle liste qui a été publiée comme proposition d'une liste internationale. Cette proposition a été discutée en profondeur au Congrès international UIS de la Chaux-de-Fonds en 1997. Elle a été votée et acceptée par des délégués nationaux.</p>
			<p>Cette liste doit servir de base internationale pour la communication. Les différents pays peuvent s'y appuyer et la compléter si besoin est par des listes annexes.</p>
			<p>Les spéléo-topographes actifs ont atteint le consensus selon lequel le plan et tous ses symboles ne représentent que la moitié du travail à faire. L'autre moitié, tout aussi importante, consiste en une description de la cavité. Cette description, présentant des faits qui ne peuvent pas être portés dans le plan, gagne ainsi en importance. Les observations sur la géologie, la sédimentologie, l'hydrologie et le climat, la flore et la faune, la description des accès et l'histoire des explorations, sans oublier la liste des équipements, font intégralement partie de la documentation écrite de la cavité. Les continuations supposées, les hypothèses et théories sur la formation de la grotte complètent les informations et donnent avec le plan une base précieuse pour les travaux futurs.</p>
			<p>Il est recommandé non seulement de dessiner un plan et une coupe longitudinale (non projetée), mais également de faire une description de la cavité comme mentionné ci-dessus.</p>
		</french>
		<german>
			<p>Am zweiten internationalen Treffen für unterirdische Topographie in Breitenbach (Schweiz) 1995 wurden die Signaturlisten der verschiedenen Länder einer Prüfung unterzogen. Die wesentlichen Symbole wurden in eine neue Liste integriert, die dann als Vorschlag für eine internationale Signaturliste veröffentlicht wurde. Dieser Vorschlag wurde dann am UIS-Kongress ausgiebig debattiert und im Anschluss von den nationalen Delegierten der UIS genehmigt.</p>
			<p>Diese Liste versteht sich als internationale Verständigungsbasis, auf dessen Grundlage die einzelnen Länder, falls dies für nötig erachtet wird, ihre eigenen Zusatzlisten aufbauen können. Es ist also nicht verboten, weitere Signaturen zu benützen!</p>
			<p>Es kristallisierte sich bei den aktiven Höhlenvermessern immer mehr heraus, dass der Plan mit allen seinen Zeichen und Signaturen immer nur die "Hälfte" der Arbeit eines Höhlenforschers darstellt. Die andere, ebenso wichtige, Hälfte besteht aus einer Beschreibung der Höhle, in der Dinge, die nicht im Plan gezeichnet werden können, niedergeschrieben werden. Die Höhlenbeschreibung erhält so einen grösseren Stellwert. Beobachtungen zur Geologie, Sedimentologie, zur Hydrologie und zum Klima, zur Flora und Fauna, dazu die Zugangsbeschreibung und ein geschichtlicher Abriss der Forschungsgeschichte, nicht zu vergessen allfällige Einrichtungslisten, all dies gehört in eine schriftliche Höhlenbeschreibung. Vermutungen über mögliche Gangfortsetzungen sowie vielleicht eine Theorie über die Höhlenentstehung runden den Text ab und machen ihn, zusammen mit dem Plan, zur wertvollen Basis für alle weiteren Arbeiten.</p>
			<p>Es ist daher dringend empfohlen, nicht nur einen Grundriss und einen (abgewickelten) Längsschnitt (siehe Akten des 9. Nationalen Kongresses 1991, Charmey) zu erstellen, sondern auch die oben erwähnte Höhlenbeschreibung!</p>
		</german>
		<italian>
			<p>Durante il "Secondo Incontro Internazionale di Topografia sotterranea" a Breitenbach (Svizzera), 1995, sono state discusse liste di simboli speleologici presentate da diversi paesi. I simboli essenziali sono stati integrati in una nuova lista e pubblicati sottoforma di proposta per una lista internazionale. Questa proposta é stata dibattuta esaurientemente al congresso dell'UIS a La Chaux de Fonds ed é stata accettata in votazione dai delegati di ogni nazione.</p>
			<p>Questa lista va interpretata come base d'intesa internazionale su cui, qualora si rendesse necessario, i singoli Paesi possono fondare la costituzione delle proprie liste accessorie.</p>
			<p>Agli speleotopografi attivi é risultato sempre piú evidente che la pianta, con tutti i suoi segni e simboli, rappresenta sempre solo la metà del lavoro d'uno speleologo. L'altra metà, altrettanto importante, é costituita da una descrizione della grotta, in cui vengono registrate cose che non possono essere disegnate nella pianta. La descrizione della grotta acquista cosí un valore di maggior importanza. Osservazioni sulla geologia, sulla sedimentologia, sull'idrologia e sul clima, sulla flora e sulla fauna, accompagnate dalla descrizione dell'accesso e da un estratto dell'istoriato esplorativo. Da non dimenticare eventuali liste degli armi; tutto ciò dev'essere contemplato nella descrizione scritta della grotta. Supposizioni su possibili continuazioni delle gallerie come pure forse una teoria sulla genesi della grotta completano il testo rendendolo, assieme alla pianta, una base preziosa per ogni ulteriore lavoro.</p>
			<p>Si raccomanda perciò di eseguire una descrizione della grotta nel senso sopracitato e non di fornire solamente il piano e la sezione della grotta (vedi documentazione del IX Congresso Internazionale di Charmey 1991).</p>
		</italian>
		<portuguese>
			<p>Durante o "Segundo Encontro Internacional de Topografia Subterrânea" em Breitenbach (Suiça), 1995, foram discutidas as listas de simbologias de diversos paises. Os símoblos essenciais foram integrados em uma nova lista e publicados como uma proposta para uma lista internacional de simbologias. Esta proposta foi debatida durante o Congresso da UIS em La Chaux de Fonds e depois votada e aceita pelos delegados nacionais de cada país.</p>
			<p>Esta lista deve ter abrangência internacional e cada país pode, se necessário, introduzir seus símbolos adicionais. Portanto não é proibido o uso de símbolos significativos adicionais.</p>
			<p>Ficou acordado entre os topógrafos e croquistas ativos que a planta com todas as feições e simbologias é apenas metade do trabalho na documentação de um sistema de cavernas. Outra parte, também muito importante é uma descrição abrangente do sistema, incluíndo feições que não podem ser representadas no mapa. Um relatório descritivo da caverna portanto é um fator importante na documentação da caverna. Observando geologia, sedimentação, condições climáticas, hidrologia, assim como a observação da fauna e flora, descrição da localização e trilha para a entrada da caverna, um resumo da história de sua exploração, e não menos importante a lista de equipamentos necessários para sua exploração, todos estes itens pertencem a uma documentação abrangente da caverna. Suposições sobre continuações de galerias, assim como teorias de sua genese completam a descrição da caverna e formam junto com um bom mapa uma importante base para trabalhos futuros.</p>
			<p>É portanto recomendado não somente se desenhar o mapa da caverna e o desenvolvimento de seção (ver documentação do 9º Congresso Nacional 1991, Charmey), mas também a descrição da caverna como comentado acima!</p>
		</portuguese>
		<romanian>
			<p>In a doua "Reuniune Internationala de Topografie Subterana"  care a avut loc in Breitenbach (Elvetia), in 1995, diferitele tipuri de liste utilizate de tari au fost discutate. Simbolurile importante au fost integrate intr-o noua lista si publicate ca si propunere a unei liste internationale. Aceasta propunere a fost discutata mai in amanunt la "Congresul International UIS" de la Chaux-de-Fonds, in 1997. Ea a fost votata si acceptata de catre delegatii fiecarei tari.</p>
			<p>Aceasta lista trebuie sa serveasca ca baza internationala pentru comunicare.  Diferitele tari pot sa o completeze  daca e nevoie, folosind propriile lor liste anexe. De aceea nu e interzisa  utilizarea  simbolurilor aditionale utile.</p>
			<p>Speotopografii activi au fost de accord cu faptul ca harta si simbolurile nu reprezinta decat jumatate din munca care trebuie facuta. Cealalta jumatate, la fel de importanta, o reprezinta descrierea  cat mai cuprinzatoare a sistemului, incluzand fenomene care nu pot fi schitate pe harta. Descrierea scrisa a pesterii este de aceea un factor foarte important in documentarea acesteia. Observarea geologiei, a sedimentelor, climatului, hidrologiei, la fel ca descrierea faunei si a florei, accesul la pestera si istoria explorarilor, fara a uita lista de  echipament necesar, toate aceste lucruri tin de o documentare scrisa cuprinzatoare a pesterii. Presupuneri ale continuarii galeriilor, ip oteze si teorii ale genezei pesterii, completeaza informatiile si dau impreuna cu o harta bine intocmita o baza valoroasa pentru munca viitoare.</p>
			<p>De aceea e recomandat nu numai sa se schiteze desenul in plan si cel longitudinal (vezi documentarea celui de-al 9-lea "Congres National" 1991, Charmey) , dar in egala masura sa se faca o descriere a pesterii asa cum a fost mentionat mai sus!</p>
		</romanian>
		<slovene>
			<p>Na drugem mednarodnem konresu podzemne topografije v Breitenbachu (Svica) leta 1995 so bili na tapeti tudi razlicni seznami znakov za risanje jamskih nacrtov, ki jih imajo posamezne drzave. Najpomembnejsi znaki so bili sprejeti v nov seznam in objavljeni kot predlog za mednarodni seznam jamskih znakov. Ta seznam so na kongresu UIS v La Chaux de Fonds delegati iz vseh drzav dodobra prediskutirali ter z glasovanjem tudi sprejeli.</p>
			<p>Seznam naj bi bila splosna mednarodna podlaga, na katero lahko vsaka dezela po zelji doda lastne nove dodatne znake. Vpeljava novih pomenonosnih znakov ni prepovedana.</p>
			<p>Dejavni merilci in risarji so v debatah ugotovili tudi, da je nacrt z vsemi svojimi znaki le polovica zadovoljive dokumentacije o jami. Drugi ravnotako pomemben del je splosen opis jamskega objekta, ki opisuje stvari, ki jih nacrt ne more vsebovati. Napisani opis je torej zelo pomemben del dokumentacije o jami. V opis spadajo: geoloska in bioloska opazovanja, pregledovanje sedimentov, klimatskih razmer, hidrologije, opis mesta nahajanja jame, poti do vhoda, kratek pregled poteka raziskav in nenazadnje seznam potrebne opreme za obisk jame. Predpostavke o moznostih nadaljevanja in teorije o nastanku posameznih rovov so skupaj z dobrim nacrtom dobra osnova za nadaljne raziskave.</p>
			<p>Zato se priporoca, da se poleg tlorisa in iztegnjenega profila jamo opise tudi z besedami.</p>
		</slovene>
		<spanish>
			<p>En el "II Encuentro Internacional de Topografía Subterránea" realizado en Breitenbach (Suiza), en 1995, las listas de símbolos cartográficos aplicados a la espeleología en diferentes países fueron objeto de discusión. Los símbolos esenciales fueron integrados en una nueva lista y publicados como una propuesta de símbolos espeleológicos internacionales. Esta propuesta fue debatida exhaustivamente en el Congreso de la UIS de La Chaux de Fonds (1997), modificada y luego votada y aceptada por los delegados de cada país.</p>
			<p>Esta lista debe ser una base internacional que permita la comprensión de mapas, en la que cada país puede, si lo considera necesario, introducir sus propios símbolos adicionales. Por lo tanto, no está prohibido el uso de símbolos significativos adicionales.</p>
			<p>Entre los topógrafos y dibujantes activos se observó después, que el mapa con todos sus símbolos y signos es sólo "la mitad" de la obra de documentación de la cueva. Otra parte, también muy importante, es una descripción completa de la cavidad, incluyendo los fenómenos que no pueden ser representados en el mapa. Un relatorio descriptivo es por lo tanto un factor muy importante en la documentación de la cueva. Debe incluir observaciones sobre la geología, los sedimentos, las condiciones climáticas, observaciones sobre la fauna y la flora, descripción de la ubicación y la ruta a la entrada de la cueva, un resumen de la historia de la exploración, y no menos importante un listado  de los equipos necesarios para su exploración. Todos estos tópicos constituyen una completa documentación de la cueva.</p>
			<p>Las hipótesis sobre las continuaciones de galerías, al igual que las teorías sobre la génesis de determinados conductos, completan la descripción de la cueva y forman junto con un buen mapa una base informativa de gran valor para las futuras labores.</p>
			<p>Por ello se recomienda, no sólo dibujar la planta de la cueva y la sección longitudinal (véase la documentación del 9° Congreso Nacional de 1991, Charmey), sino también elaborar una descripción de la cueva como se mencionó antes!.</p>
		</spanish>
		<turkish>
			<p>1995 yılında Breitenbach (İsviçre) yapılan II. Uluslararası Yeraltı Topoğrafyası Çalıştayında, değişik ülkelere ait Mağara Sembollerinin listeleri tartışılmıştır. Temel alınan semboller yeni bir liste altında toplanmış ve uluslararası mağara sembolleri listesi olarak önerilmiştir. Bu öneri La Chaux de Fonds’da UMB kongresinde tartışılmış, daha sonra her  üye ülkenin delegesi tarafından oylanarak kabul edilmiştir.</p>
			<p>Bu liste ayrıntılı, uluslararası destekli, bir ülke için gerekli ise kendilerine ait ek sembollerin tanıtıldığı bir liste olmalıdır. Bu yüzden anlamlı ek sembollerin kullanılması engellenmemiştir.</p>
			<p>Etkin araştırıcıların ve teknik ressamlar ile oluşturulan bütün sembollerin ve işaretlerin planı bir mağara sisteminin belgeleme çalışmasının yarısını oluşturmaktadır. Geriye kalan en önemli bölüm ise çizim ile anlatılamayacak olgu olan sistemin ayrıtılı tanımlanmasıdır. Yazılı mağara tanımlamaları bu yüzden oldukça önemlidir. Bitki ve hayvan gözlemleri, mağaranın bulunduğu yer ve giriş ağzına giden yolun tanımlanması, araştırmanın tarihçesi, gerekli minimun malzemenin listesi kadar jeolojik gözlemler, sedimanlar, mağaradaki hava koşulları ayrıntılı mağara belgelemesinde bulunmalıdır.</p>
			<p>Galerilerin sürekli olduğunun varsayımı aynı şekilde belirgin galerilerin oluşumuna ait teoriler mağara tanımlamasını oluşturmakta, iyi yapılmış bir mağara haritası ile birlikte gelecekteki çalışmalar için değerli bir temel oluşturmaktadır.</p>
			<p>Bu yüzden yanlız mağara plan ve kesit belgelemesi değil (9. Ulusal Kongre 1991, Charmey), ayrıca yukarıda, mağaraların sözü edilen tanımlamalarıda dikkate alınmalıdır!</p>
		</turkish>
	</text>
	<text id="aboutTheAuthor">
		<croatian>
			<p>Radna skupina je nastala na medunarodnom skupu podzemne topografije, gdje su se poceli pregledavati i standardizirati postojeci simboli. Rezultat rada grupe je ovdje predstavljen sluzbeni skup simbola za crtanje speleoloskih objekata. Prilikom rada dotaknuti su mnogobrojni problemi kao npr.:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Uporaba racunala pri crtanju nacrta (CAD i DTP paketi)</li>
				<li>Standardizirana debljina crte</li>
				<li>Izbor standardne palete boja (sa obzirom na razvoj programa)</li>
				<li>Pokusaj uspostave svjetskog standarda preciznosti i tocnosti</li>
			</ul>
			<p>Te probleme trebala bi rjesavati radna grupa unutar Informacijske komisije UIS u bliskoj suradnji sa International Geographical Union i ostalim institucijama. Namjena radne grupe je uspostava zbirke medunarodnih standarda koji bi uredili nacrte da budu citljivi svakome.</p>
		</croatian>
		<dutch>
			<p>This working group results of the "International Meetings on Subterrainean Topography" that began to verify and standardize already the existing conventional signs. The results are the official UIS symbol list presented here. During this work we`ve been faced with many other linked problems, such as:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>the use of computer software to draw plans (CAD and DTP-Packages)</li>
				<li>standardise the line thicknesses</li>
				<li>choose a standard set of colours (in view of the progress of computer plans)</li>
				<li>try to establish a worldwide standard of precision and accuracy</li>
			</ul>
			<p>This will be done as a working group within the UIS Informatics Commission and in close liason with the International Geographical Union and other institutions. The aim of the working group is to establish a set of international standards in order to make maps readable for everybody.</p>
		</dutch>
		<english>
			<p>This working group results of the "International Meetings on Subterrainean Topography" that began to verify and standardize already the existing conventional signs. The results are the official UIS symbol list presented here. During this work we`ve been faced with many other linked problems, such as:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>the use of computer software to draw plans (CAD and DTP-Packages)</li>
				<li>standardise the line thicknesses</li>
				<li>choose a standard set of colours (in view of the progress of computer plans)</li>
				<li>try to establish a worldwide standard of precision and accuracy</li>
			</ul>
			<p>This will be done as a working group within the UIS Informatics Commission and in close liason with the International Geographical Union and other institutions. The aim of the working group is to establish a set of international standards in order to make maps readable for everybody.</p>
		</english>
		<french>
			<p>Ce groupe de travail résulte des "Rencontres Internationales de topographie souterraine" qui a commencé à vérifier et à standardiser les signes conventionnels déjà existants. La liste des symboles representée ici est le résultat de leur travail. Cependant d'autres choses restent encore à faire, notamment:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>l'usage de l'ordinateur pour le dessin (CAD software)</li>
				<li>standardiser les épaisseurs des lignes</li>
				<li>choisir une gamme de couleurs (en vue des plans ordinateur)</li>
				<li>établir un standard de précision</li>
			</ul>
			<p>Ces travaux vont être effectués par ce groupe de travail au sein de l 'UIS Informatics Commission et en contact avec la International Geographical Union et d'autres institutions. Le but de ce groupe est d'établir des standards internationaux pour rendre les plans lisibles pour tout le monde.</p>
		</french>
		<german>
			<p>Diese Arbeitsgruppe resultiert aus dem "Internationalen Treffen über unterirdische Topographie" die sich die Standardisierung und Vereinheitlichung der bereits existierenden Höhlenplansignaturen zum Ziel gesetzt hat. Das Resultat ist die hier präsentierte offizielle UIS-Symbolliste. Im Zuge dieser Arbeiten wurden wir mit ein paar anderen, z.T. nahe verwandten Problemen konfrontiert, denen sich die Arbeitsgruppe in Zukunft ebenfalls widmen will:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Computergestützte Höhlenplanzeichnung (CAD und DTP-Pakete)</li>
				<li>Standardisierung der Strichstärken</li>
				<li>Standardisierung des Farbeinsatzes bei Höhlenplänen (gerade in Bezug auf Computereinsatz)</li>
				<li>Versuch, einen weltweiten Genauigkeits- und Qualitätsstandard einzuführen</li>
			</ul>
			<p>Dies soll mit einer Arbeitsgruppe als Subkommission der UIS Informatik-Kommission geschehen in Zusammenarbeit mit der Internationalen Geographischen Union (IGU) und anderen Institutionen. Das Ziel ist ein Set von internationalen Standards zu entwickeln, um Höhlenpläne für jedermann lesbar zu machen.</p>
		</german>
		<italian>
			<p>Questo gruppo di lavoro è espressione del "Incontro Internazionale di Topografia Sotterranea" ed ha cercato di verificare e standardizzare i segni convenzionali attualmente esistenti. Il risultato è la lista ufficiale dei simboli qui presentata. Durante questo lavoro abbiamo dovuto fare faccia a diversi problemi congiunti come:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>l'uso di programmi informatici per disegnare i piani (CAD e DTP- Packages)</li>
				<li>spessore standardizzato delle linee</li>
				<li>scelta di una lista di colori standard (in vista dei progressi dei piani computerizzati)</li>
				<li>cercare di stabilire uno standard unico di precisione e accuratezza</li>
			</ul>
			<p>sar… fatto nel quadro di un gruppo all'interno della Commissione di Informatica dell' UIS e in stretta collaborazione con l'Unione Internazinale di Geografia ed altre istituzioni. Lo scopo di questo gruppo di lavoro é  la definizione di norme internazionali cosí da rendere accessibile a tutti la lettura delle carte.</p>
		</italian>
		<portuguese>
			<p>Este grupo de trabalho resulta dos "Encontros Internacionais de Topografia Subterrânea" que começou a verificar e padronizar as convenções e simbologias já existentes. O resultado foi a lista de simbologia oficial da UIS aqui apresentada. Durante a realização deste trabalho nós nos confrontamos com muitos outros problemas relacionados, como por exemplo: o uso de programas de computador para se desenhar os mapas (CAD e Pacotes-DTP), padronização de grossura da linha, escolha de padrões de cores (no caso de uso mapas digitais),tentativa de se estabelecer um padrão mundial de precisão e acurácia.</p>
			<p>Isto será realizado através de um grupo de trabalho na Comissão de Informática da UIS com estreita colaboração da União Geográfica Internacional e outras instituições. O alvo deste grupo de trabalho é estabelecer um conjunto de padrões internacionais para a confecção de mapas compreensíveis por todos.</p>
		</portuguese>
		<romanian>
			<p>Acest grup de lucru e rezultatul �Intalnirilor Internationale de Topografie Subterana�  care a inceput sa verifice si sa standardizeze semnele conventionale deja existente. Lista de simboluri prezentate aici e rezultatul muncii lor. In timpul acesteia s-au confruntat cu alte probleme, cum ar fi:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>folosirea unui software pentru desenarea hartilor  (CAD software)</li>
				<li>standardizarea grosimii liniilor</li>
				<li>alegerea unui set  de culori standard (in vederea evoluarii hartilor pe calculator)</li>
				<li>stabilirea unui standard de precizie</li>
			</ul>
			<p>Acestea vor fi realizate de catre un grup de lucru din cadrul Comisiei de Informatica a UIS, in stransa legatura cu Uniunea Geografica  Internationala si alte institutii. Sarcina  grupului de lucru e sa stabileasca un set de standarde internationale, cu scopul de a face ca hartile sa fie intelese de catre toata lumea.</p>
		</romanian>
		<slovene>
			<p>Delovna skupina je nastala na mednarodnem srecanju podzemne topografije, kjer se je zacelo pregledovati in standardizirati obstojece dogovorjene znake. Rezultat dela skupine je tu predstavljen uradni nabor znakov za risanje jam. Med samim delom, smo bili sooceni z mnogimi sorodnimi problemi kot naprimer:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Uporaba racunalnika pri risanju nacrtov (cad in dtp-pakteti)</li>
				<li>Standardizirati debelino crte</li>
				<li>Izbrati standarden nabor barv (z ozirom na razvoj racunalniskih programov)</li>
				<li>Poskus vzpostavitve vsesvetovnega standarda preciznosti in natancnosti</li>
			</ul>
			<p>Te probleme naj bi resevala delovna skupina znotraj Informacijske komisije UIS v tesni povezavi z International Geographical Union in ostalimi institucijami. Namen delovne skupine je vzpostaviti zbirko mednarodnih standardov, ki bi naredili nacrte berljive vsakomur.</p>
		</slovene>
		<spanish>
			<p>Este grupo de trabajo es el resultado de los "Encuentros Internacionales sobre Topografía Subterránea" que comenzaron a verificar y estandarizar los símbolos convencionales existentes. El resultado es la lista oficial de símbolos de la UIS que se presenta aquí. Durante este trabajo, hemos tenido que enfrentar muchos otros problemas relacionados, tales como:</p>
        	<ul>
				<li>El uso de programas informáticos para dibujar planos ( CAD y paquetes de diseño gráfico Desktop-Publishing DTP)</li>
				<li>estandarizar el grosor de las líneas</li>
				<li>elegir un conjunto estándar de colores (acorde a los avances en la edición de planos usando un ordenador)</li>
				<li>tratar de establecer un estándar mundial de precisión y exactitud</li>
			</ul>
			<p>Esto será realizado a través de un grupo de trabajo dentro de la Comisión de Informática de la UIS y en estrecha cooperación con la Unión Geográfica Internacional y otras instituciones afines. El objetivo del grupo de trabajo es establecer un conjunto de normas internacionales con el fin de hacer los mapas comprensibles para todos.</p>
		</spanish>		
		<turkish>
			<p>This working group results of the "International Meetings on Subterrainean Topography" that began to verify and standardize already the existing conventional signs. The results are the official UIS symbol list presented here. During this work we`ve been faced with many other linked problems, such as:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>bilgisayar programlarının planların çizilmesi için kullanılması (CAD ve DTP-Paketleri)</li>
				<li>çizgi kalınlıklarının standartlaştırılması</li>
				<li>standart renklerin seçimi (bilgisayar planlarının geliştirilmesinin değerlendirilmesi)</li>
				<li>dünya çapında doğru ve hassas bir standartın kurulması</li>
			</ul>
			<p>This will be done as a working group within the UIS Informatics Commission and in close liason with the International Geographical Union and other institutions. The aim of the working group is to establish a set of international standards in order to make maps readable for everybody.</p>
		</turkish>
	</text>
</texts>
