identifier§flag(1 is not cut)§english§german§french§italian§slovene§croatian§romanian§dutch§czech§slovak§english_text§german_text§french_text§italian_text§Slovene_text§croatian_text§romanian_text§dutch_text§czech_text§slovak_textsurvey_points§0§Survey Points§Messpunkte§Point de relevé principal§Caposaldo principale§Merilne tocke§Mjerne tocke§Punct topografic principal§Meetpunten§§§The main survey points have been kept in the list, but often they are no longer shown on fair copies.§Die Messpunkte sind noch in der Liste verblieben, obwohl sie vielfach in den Reinzeichnungen nicht mehr verwendet werden§Les principaux points de relevé ont été gardés dans la liste, bien qu'ils soient souvent supprimés sur les topographies définitives.§I capisaldi principali sono stati mantenuti nella simbologia, ma /egraven facoltativo riportarli sul rilievo finale.§Glavne merilne tocke so ostale v seznamu, vendar se jih na nacrte pogosto ne rise vec. §Glavne mjerne tocke ostale su na popisu simbola, iako se cesto prikazuju samo na radnom orginalu.§The main survey points have been kept in the list, but often they are no longer shown on fair copies.§De hoofdmeetpunten worden meestal niet meer afgebeeld, maar ze blijven bewaard in een lijst.§§§outline_gallery§0§Outline of a Gallery§Gangumriss§Dessin de galerie§Contorno della cavitr§Stene rova§Stijene kanala/ galerije§Conturul gaeriei§gang-omlijning§§§as before§wie zuvor§Comme auparavant§invariato§Kot do zdaj.§Kao i do sada.§as before§Spreekt voor zich.§§§underlying_gallery§0§Underlying Passage§Unterlagernde Gänge§Croisement de galeries§Cavitr sottoposta§Spodaj lezeci rov§Kanal na nizoj etazi§Galerii suprapuse§Onderliggende gang§§§As an additional help to distinguish the lower from the upper passage it is recommended to stop the line of the lower gallery before it reaches the upper gallery. To distinguish this symbol from the "presumed dimensions of space" (see below) it is recommended to draw short dashes with wide spacing.§Als zusätzliche Hilfe, um unterlagernde von den Gängen darüber zu unterscheiden, wird empfohlen, die Linie des unterlagernden Ganges kurz vor dem Gang darüber abzusetzen. Um Verwechslungen mit den "Geschätzten Gangdimensionen" zu vermeiden, wird empfohlen, mit kurzen Strichen und weiten Abständen dazwischen zu zeichnen.§De façon r distinguer la galerie inférieure de la galerie supérieure, il est recommandé d'interrompre le dessin de la galerie inférieure avant qu'elle ne croise la supérieure. Pour distinguer ce symbole de celui des "Dimensions spatiales présumées" (voir ci-dessous) il est recommandé de dessiner des pointillés courts largement espacés.§Come indicazione ulteriore per distinguere la cavitr sottostante dalla sovrapposta, si raccomanda di fermare la linea di contorno della cavitr sottoposta prima di raggiungere il contornodella cavitr sovrapposta. Per distinguere questo simbolo da quello di dimensioni presunte della cavitr (vedi sotto), si raccomanda di disegnare il tratteggio mediante tratti corti con ampia spaziatura.§Da bi se spodaj lezeci rov lazje locilo od zgornjega, se svetuje, da se crto spodnjega rova zakljuci malo preden doseze steno zgornjega rova. Da bi se ta znak locilo od znaka za predvideno velikost prostora (spodaj), morajo biti crtice kratke, prekinitve pa dolge.§Da bi se kanal na nizoj etazi jace razlikovao od gornjeg kanala, preporuka je da se kanal na nizoj etazi prestane crtati i prije nego li se dodirne sa gornjim kanalom. Da bi se ovaj simbol jace razlikovao od simbola za pretpostavljenu velicinu galerije (nize), preporuca se da crte budu krace, a razmaci siri.§As an additional help to distinguish the lower from the upper passage it is recommended to stop the line of the lower gallery before it reaches the upper gallery. To distinguish this symbol from the "presumed dimensions of space" (see below) it is recommended to draw short dashes with wide spacing.§Om de lagere gang te kunnen onderscheiden van de hogere gang, is het aan te raden om de lijnen van de lagere gang te stoppen voordat ze de hogere gang raken. Om dit lijntype te onderscheiden van de “geschatte maten van de ruimte” (zie daar) is het aan te raden om korte streepjes te tekenen met grote tussenruimten.§§§too_narrow_continuation§0§Too narrow Continuation§Fortsetzung zu eng§Continuations trop étroites§Prosecuzione troppo stretta§Preozko nadaljevanje§Preuski prolaz§Impenetrabil§te nauwe doorgang§§§as before§wie zuvor§Comme auparavant.§invariato §Kot do zdaj.§Kao i do sada.§as before§Spreekt voor zich.§§§continuation_possible§0§continuation Possible§Fortsetzung möglich§Continuation possible§Prosecuzione possibile§Mozno nadaljevanje§Moguci nastavak§Continuare posibila§mogelijke doorgang§§§as before§wie zuvor§Comme auparavant.§invariato§Kot do zdaj.§Kao i do sada.§as before§Spreekt voor zich.§§§presumed_dimension_space§0§Presumed dimensions of space§Geschätzte Gangdimensionen§Dimensions spatiales présumées§Dimensioni presunte della cavitr§Predvidena veliksot prostora§Pretpostavljena velicina kanala/ galerije§Dimensiuni spatiale presupuse§Geschatte maten van de ruimte§§§as before. The dashes should be long and the spacing narrow (see "underlying passages").§Wie zuvor. Die Striche sollten lang sein und die Abstände dazwischen kurz. (vergl. "Unterlagernde Gänge")§Comme auparavant. Il est recommandé de dessiner des pointillés longs faiblement espacés (voir ci-dessus "Croisement de galeries").§invariato. Per distinguere questo simbolo da quello di cavitr sottoposta, i tratti devono essere lunghi, con spaziatura breve.§Kot do zdaj. Da ne bi prihajalo do mesanja z znakom za spodaj lezec rov, morajo biti crtice dolge in prekinitve kratke.§Kao i do sada. Da ne bi doslo do mijesanja sa simbolom za kanal na vise etaza, crtice bi trebale biti duge, a razmaci kratki.§as before. The dashes should be long and the spacing narrow (see "underlying passages").§Spreekt voor zich. De streepjes moeten lang en de ruimte ertussen klein zijn (zie “onderliggende gangen”).§§§ceiling_form§0§Ceiling form§Deckenform§Forme du plafond§Morfologia del soffitto§Oblika stropa§Oblik stropa§Forma tavanului§vorm van het plafond§§§The symbol for the form of the ceiling of a cave is also used for the dripline and for chimneys.§Das gleiche Symbol wird auch für Trauflinie und Schlote verwendet.§Le symbole pour décrire le plafond d'une cavité est aussi utilisé pour "Entrée de cavité" et "Cheminée" (voir ci-dessous).§Questo simbolo viene anche usato per il "limite esterno della grotta" e per il "camino"§Ta zank se uporablja tudi za prikaz zunanjih mej jame in kamine.§Ovaj simbol koristi se takoder i za okapnicu (pocetak spilje) i dimnjake.§The symbol for the form of the ceiling of a cave is also used for the dripline and for chimneys.§Het symbool voor de vorm van het plafond wordt ook gebruikt voor druplijnen en voor schoorstenen.§§§dripline_profile§0§Dripline - Profile§Trauflinie - Querschnitt§Entrée de cavité - Sections transversales§Limite esterno della grotta - Sezione trasversal§Zunanja meja jame - profil§kapnica (pocetak spilje) - Presjek§Intrare-sectiune transversala§druplijn - profiel§§§The dripline can give valuable information especially for smaller caves and overhangs. It describes the actual entrance to a cave including the upper ceiling region and should therefore not be omitted. At the dripline the cave begins.<BR><BR>Cross-sections are of major importance for the understanding of a passage. For each map passage cross-sections must be drawn. The arrows indicating the direction of view are done differently, a clear indication is, however, necessary.§Die Trauflinie (Höhleneingang) gibt wertvolle Hinweise v.a. für kleinere Höhlen und Überhänge. Sie beschreibt den eigentlichen Eingang inklusive der Höhlendecke und soll deshalb nicht weggelassen werden. An der Trauflinie beginnt die Höhle.<BR><BR>Querschnitte sind wichtig für das Verständnis eines Höhlenganges und oftmals auch dessen Genese. Sie dürfen deshalb in keinem sorgfältig erstelltem Höhlenplan fehlen. Die Pfeile, die die Blickrichtung anzeigen, werden unterschiedlich gezeichnet. Eine klarer Hinweis ist deshalb wichtig.§Entrée de cavité: Les formes d'entrée de cavité peuvent donner des informations utiles, spécialement pour les petites cavités et les surplombs. Une ligne pointillée décrit l'entrée de la cavité y compris le plafond de l'entrée et ne doit pas etre omis. La cavité commence r cette ligne d'escarpement.<BR><BR>Sections transversales: Ces profils sont de premicre importance dans la compréhension d'une galerie. Ils doivent etre dessinés pour chaque galerie. Les flcches indiquant la direction de vue peuvent etre dessinées de façon différente, une description claire étant de toute façon nécessaire.§<B>Limite esterno della grotta:</B> La posizione del limite esterno della grotta pun fornire importanti indicazioni, soprattutto per cavitr minori e ripari sotto-roccia. Con essa si descrive la proiezione sul suolo del tracciato dell'inizio della volta della cavitr. <P><B>Sezione trasversale:</B> Le sezioni trasversali sono molto importanti per comprendere la forma della cavitr. Per ogni ambiente topografato devono essere realizzate una o piu sezioni trasversali. Le frecce che indicano la direzione di vista possono essere realizzate con stili diversi, ma un'indicazione chiara c comunque necessaria.§Nacrt zunanjih mej jame lahko da pomembne informacije, zlasti pri manjsih jamah in spodmolih. Meja stropa, ki ga oznacuje, je dejanski zacetek jame, zato tega znaka ne velja izpuscati. <BR><BR> Risanje profila daje pomembne podatke o rovu samem, zato jih je treba vedno risati. Obstaja vec oblik puscice, ki oznacuje smer profila, pomembno je le, da se na nacrtu jasno vidi, kaj profil predstavlja.§Okapnica daje vrijedne podatke, pogotovo za manje spilje i poluspilje. Granica stropa koju opisuje ovaj simbol je stvarni pocetak spilje i zbog toga se ovaj simbol ne bi smio ispustati.<BR><BR>Presjeci su vrlo vazni za razumjevanje oblika kanala (galerije) stoga je potrebno za svaki nacrtani kanal,  nacrtati i presjek. Postoji vise oblika strelice koja oznacava smjer pogleda presjeka, no bitna je jasna indikacija sto presjek predstavlja.§The dripline can give valuable information especially for smaller caves and overhangs. It describes the actual entrance to a cave including the upper ceiling region and should therefore not be omitted. At the dripline the cave begins.<BR><BR>Cross-sections are of major importance for the understanding of a passage. For each map passage cross-sections must be drawn. The arrows indicating the direction of view are done differently, a clear indication is, however, necessary.§Speciaal voor kleinere grotten en overhangen kan een druplijn waardevolle informatie geven. De druplijn  beschrijft de werkelijke ingang van een grot inclusief de hogere plafond regionen en mag daarom niet worden verwaarloosd. Bij de druplijn begint de grot. <BR><BR> Dwarsdoorsnedes zijn belangrijk om de passage te verduidelijken. Bij elke getekende gang moeten dwarsdoorsnedes getekend worden. Teken bij de plaats waar de dwarsdoorsnede is, pijlen die  de kijkrichting aangeven. Dit is belangrijk.§§§step§0§Steps§Stufen§Marches, ressauts§Salto§Stopnja§Skok§Saritoare§treden§§§This symbol is well known, just don't forget that the little dashes are always to be orientated downwards!§Diese Signatur ist recht bekannt. Vergiss nicht, die Zacken auf der Seite des Abgrunds zu plazieren.§Ce symbole est trcs connu, mais n'oubliez pas que les petites hachures sont toujours orientées vers le bas!§Questo simbolo c ben noto; c semplicemente necessario ricordare che i trattini sono orientati verso la porzione ribassata del salto. La misura dell'altezza del salto va riportata in metri.§To je dobro znan znak. Pomembno: kratke crtice morajo biti usmerjene proti dnu stopnje. Velikost stopnje se podaja v metrih.§Dobro poznat simbol. Bitno je voditi racuna da su crtice su uvijek usmjerene prema dnu skoka. Visina skoka je u metrima.§This symbol is well known, just don't forget that the little dashes are always to be orientated downwards!§Dit symbool is erg bekend. Vergeet niet dat de kleine streepjes altijd naar beneden wijzen.§§§pit§0§Pit§Schacht§Puits (profondeur en mctres)§Pozzo§Brezno§Vertikalni kanal (jama u objektu)§Put (adâncime în metri)§Put/schacht§§§The filled or empty triangle have been replaced by dashed lines for two reasons: First, the dashed line is easier to draw, secondly it is unclear even to most draughtsmen whether the empty triangles represent the smaller or the higher steps or when they should be filled (at 5 m or 10 m?).§Die leeren und gefüllten Dreiecke wurden aus zwei Gründen ersetzt: Erstens ist die jetzige Variante einfacher zu zeichnen, zweitens ist es für viele Zeichner auch unklar, ob die leeren Dreiecke die höheren oder die niedrigeren Stufen repräsentieren und wo der Schwellwert liegt, um sie zu füllen (bei 50 oder 10 m ?).§Les triangles pleins ou vides ont été remplacés par des hachures pour deux raisons : Premicrement, les hachures sont plus faciles r dessiner, deuxicmement, il n'était pas clair, meme pour la majorité des dessinateurs, de savoir si les triangles vides représentaient des petits ou des grands dénivelés ni r partir de quelle hauteur les remplir (r 5 m ou 10 m ?).§I triangolini vuoti o pieni della precedente simbologia sono stati sostituiti con semplici trattini per due motivi: i trattini sono piu semplici da disegnare e la maggior parte dei rilevatori non aveva chiaro l'uso dei triangolini vuoti piuttosto che pieni.§Prazni in zapolnjeni trikotniki so bili zamenjani z docrtanimi crtami zaradi dveh razlogov. Prvic se docrtano crto lazje narise in drugic si  vecina merilcev niti ni bila na jasnem, kaksna je razlika med polnimi in praznimi trikotniki.§Puni ili prazni trokutici zamijenjeni su crticama iz dva razloga. Kao prvo, crtice je lakse nacrtati, a kao drugo, vecini mjernika nije bilo jasno koja je razlika izmedu punih i praznih trokutica.§The filled or empty triangle have been replaced by dashed lines for two reasons: First, the dashed line is easier to draw, secondly it is unclear even to most draughtsmen whether the empty triangles represent the smaller or the higher steps or when they should be filled (at 5 m or 10 m?).§Om twee redenen zijn de gevulde of lege driehoek vervangen door streepjes. In de eerste plaats omdat  streepjes makkelijker te tekenen zijn. Ten tweede is het onduidelijk, zelfs voor de meeste tekenaars, of de lege driehoekjes nu de kleinere of juist de grotere treden weergeven en wanneer ze gevuld moeten zijn (bij 5 of 10 m?)§§§pit_surface§0§Pit open to Surface§Schacht mit Oberflächenöffnung§Puits débouchant en surface§Pozzo 2§Vhodno brezno§Vertikalni ulaz (otvor jame)§Aven§Put, Daglichtput§§§as before§wie zuvor§Comme auparavant§invariato§Kot do zdaj.§Kao i do sada.§as before§Spreekt voor zich.§§§chimney_pit§0§Aven/Aven-pitchs§Schacht - Schlot§Cheminée-Puits-cheminée§Camino - Pozzo-Camino§Kamin - brezno s kaminom§Dimnjak/ Dimnjak iznad jame§Horn - Horn-put§schoorsteen - put§§§The plus and minus signs can be written inside or outside the cave. For reasons of clearness they should be encircled when written outside the cave. We agreed to the following procedure to indicate the difficulty of a drop or a pitch: If the drop can be climbed without gear, there is only the number (in meters) written. If gear is needed, any letter precedes the number. This way, the use of most countries is respected. It is  optional to draw the anchor points and ropes into the longitudinal section.§Das Plus/Minus-Zeichen kann innerhalb oder ausserhalb der Höhle gezeichnet werden. Um Unklarheiten vorzubeugen, sollten die Zeichen, wenn sie ausserhalb der Höhle plaziert werden, innerhalb eines Kreises stehen. Wir vereinbarten die folgende Vorgehensweise, um die Tiefe eines Schachtes oder Schlotes zu bestimmen: Wenn der Schlot ohne technische Ausrüstung geklettert werden kann, so wird nur die Nummer (in Metern) angeschrieben. Wenn technisches Material benötigt wird, so wird ein Buchstabe (z.B. P) der Zahl vorangestellt. Dabei werden die Gepflogenheiten der meisten Länder respektiert. Es bleibt dem Zeichner überlassen, allenfalls noch Ankerpunkte (Spits etc) und den Seilverlauf einzuzeichnen.§Les signes + et - peuvent etre écrits en dedans ou en dehors du dessin de la cavité. Pour des raisons de clarté ils doivent etre entourés d'un cercle quand ils sont dessinés en dehors. Nous avons adopté la procédure suivante pour indiquer la difficulté d'un ressaut ou d'un puits : si le ressaut peut s'escalader en libre, on écrit seulement la hauteur (en mctres) ; s'il faut du matériel, la hauteur est précédée d'une lettre quelconque. Ainsi les habitudes de la plupart des pays sont respectées. Il est facultatif de dessiner les points d'ancrage et les cordes dans les coupes longitudinales.§I segni piu e meno possono essere disposti sia all'interno, sia all'esterno della cavitr. Per motivi di comprensione, andranno inseriti in un cerchio quando sono disposti all'esterno della cavitr.<P><I>C stata stabilita la seguente procedura per indicare la profonditr di una verticale: se il salto/pozzo/camino pun essere arrampicato senza attrezzature, viene indicato il solo numero (in metri) che rappresenta il dislivello. Se c necessaria attrezzatura, qualsiasi lettera precede il numero. In questo modo c possibile mantenere in vigore le diverse convenzioni nazionali, pur conservando la comprensibilitr complessiva. C facoltativo disegnare i punti di attacco e la disposizione delle corde.</I>§Znaka plus in minus sta lahko narisana tudi izven jame, vendar morata biti v tem primeru zaradi jasnosti obkrozena. Za oznacitev zahtevnosti brezna predlagamo sledece: ce je brezno ali stopnja prostopreplezljiva, se za oznacitev globine brezna napise le stevilko brez crke, ce pa spust v brezno zahteva opremo, se pred stevilko doda katerokoli crko. Na ta nacin hkrati spostujemo posamezne nacionalne dogovore. V stranski ris brezna lahko dorisemo se pritrdisca in vrvi.§Znakovi plus  i minus mogu biti nacrtani unutar ili izvan objekta, u kojem slucaju bi trebali biti zaokruzeni (zbog jasnoce). Da bi se oznacila tezina skoka predlaze se: ako se jama ili dimnjak moze ispenjati bez opreme (slobodno), samo se ispise visina u metrima, a ukoliko su potrebna tehnicka pomagala pred visinu skoka se doda bilo koje slovo. Na taj nacin respektirani su simboli vecine zemalja. Opcionalno se mogu ucrtati spitovi i uzad u ispruzeni profil.§The plus and minus signs can be written inside or outside the cave. For reasons of clearness they should be encircled when written outside the cave. We agreed to the following procedure to indicate the difficulty of a drop or a pitch: If the drop can be climbed without gear, there is only the number (in meters) written. If gear is needed, any letter precedes the number. This way, the use of most countries is respected. It is  optional to draw the anchor points and ropes into the longitudinal section.§De plus en min tekens kunnen binnen of buiten de grot geschreven worden. Voor de duidelijkheid worden ze omcirkeld als ze buiten de grot geschreven zijn. De volgende afspraken geven de moeilijkheid van de put aan; Als de put beklommen kan worden zonder materiaal, dan wordt de put alleen aangegeven met de diepte in meters. Is materiaal noodzakelijk, dan wordt de diepte voorafgegaan door een letter. Deze manier is in de meeste landen aanvaard. Optioneel kunnen de touwen en ankerpunten in de verticale doorsnede getekend worden.§§§contour_lines§1§Contourlines§Höhenkurven§Courbes de niveau§Curve di livello§Izohipse§Slojnice sa oznacenom nadmorskom visinom§Curbe de nivel (altitudine în metri)§Contourlijnen§§§Contour Lines (lines of same altitude) with altimetric measurement as done on geographic maps are seldom used, as the exact ground level is not always easily established and precise drawings can cause serious problems. Gradient lines are used more frequently.§Höhenkurven (Isohypsen) mit der gemessenen Höhe über Meer, wie sie in topographischen Karten üblich sind, werden selten verwendet, da die exakte Höhe vielmals schwer zu bestimmen ist. Gefällelinien, die den Verlauf von abfallenden Gängen veranschaulichen, sind allerdings ziemlich gebräuchlich.§Les isohypses (ou courbes de niveau) avec indication de l'altitude comme on en trouve sur les cartes géographiques sont rarement utilisées, du fait que le niveau exact du sol n'est pas facilement déterminable et qu'un dessin précis pose de sérieux problcmes. Des lignes représentant les gradients d'altitude sont plus souvent utilisées.§Le isoipse (linee che collegano i punti posti alla medesima quota) con quota altimetrica sul livello del mare, come si usa per le carte topografiche, vengono raramente usate nel rilievo ipogeo, dato che spesso non c facile stabilire la quota del terreno e il disegno preciso pun causare seri problemi. Vengono usate molto piu frequentemente le linee di gradiente.§Izohipse (crte, ki povezujejo tocke z doloceno nadmorsko visino) s podatki o nadmorski visini so redko uporabljane, ker je natancno meritev tal pogosto tezko opraviti, natancen nacrt pa je le se vecji problem. Pogosteje se uporablja crte, ki kazejo naklon.§Slojnice (linije koje spajaju tocke iste nadmorske visine) sa oznacenom visinom, kao na zemljovidu,  rijetko se koriste, jer je tesko utvrditi tocnu visinu tla, a precizan crtezi je jos veci problem. Cesce se koriste slojnice bez oznacene visine.§Contour Lines (lines of same altitude) with altimetric measurement as done on geographic maps are seldom used, as the exact ground level is not always easily established and precise drawings can cause serious problems. Gradient lines are used more frequently.§Hoogtelijnen met hoogtegetallen zoals op topografische kaarten staan afgebeeld worden zelden gebruikt. Het exacte bodemverloop is niet altijd gemakkelijk te bepalen en het geeft grote moeilijkheden om dit nauwkeurig te tekenen. Overgangslijnen worden meer gebruikt.§§§gradient_arrows§1§Gradient Arrows - Entrance Arrow§Gefällepfeile - Eingangspfeil§Flcche de gradient - Flcche indiquant l'entrée de la cavité§Freccia di gradiente - Freccia per l'ingresso§Smer naklona - puscica za vhod§Smjer nagiba - Ulazna strelica§Directia de panta-Saggeata indicând intrarea§Daal-pijlen Ingangs-pijl§T§§he differentiation between gradient arrows inside and outside the cave is now omitted. An arrow indicating the entrance was added to the list.§Die Unterscheidung zwischen Gefällepfeilen innerhalb und ausserhalb der Höhle wurde weggelassen. Ein Pfeil, der den Eingang anzeigt, wurde hinzugefügt.§La différentiation entre flcches de gradient r l'intérieur et r l'extérieur de la cavité a été supprimée. Une flcche indiquant l'entrée a été ajoutée r la liste.§La distinzione fra frecce di gradiente interne od esterne alla cavitr viene abolita. Viene invece aggiunta una freccia per indicare l'ingresso della cavitr.§Razlike med naklonskimi puscicami izven in znotraj jame so bile opuscene. Dodana je bila puscica, ki oznacuje vhod jame.§Ne postoje vise razlicite strelice koje bi oznacavale smjer nagiba unutar i izvan objekta.Dodana je strelica koja oznacava ulaz u objekt.§The differentiation between gradient arrows inside and outside the cave is now omitted. An arrow indicating the entrance was added to the list.§Het verschil tussen de daalpijlen binnen en buiten de grot is nu te negeren. Een pijl die de grotingang aangeeft is toegevoegd aan de lijst§§§gradient_lines§1§Gradient Lines§Gefällelinien§Lignes de gradient§Linee di Gradiente§Naklonske crte§Slojnice (nagibne linije)§Linie de panta§Overgangslijnen§§§Gradient lines are the most common methods to illustrate the ground structure. As on geographic maps narrow spacing indicates a steep and wide spacing a gentle slope.§Gefällelinien sind der gebräuchlichste Weg, die Bodenstruktur von Gängen und Hallen zu beschreiben. Wie auf topographischen Karten gilt, dass enger gereihte Gefällelinien ein steileres Gelände anzeigen als weiter gesetzte.§Les lignes de gradient sont la méthode la plus utilisée pour illustrer la structure du sol. Comme sur les cartes géographiques, un espacement serré correspond r une pente raide, un espacement plus lâche, r une faible pente.§Le linee di gradiente sono il metodo piu&grave; comune per illustrare la struttura del suolo. Come su una carta geografica, linee ravvicinate indicano una forte pendenza, mentre linee distanziate indicano una pendenza minore.§Naklonske crte so najobicajnejsa metoda prikazovanja oblike tal. Kot na zemljevidih tudi tu manjsi razmak med crtama oznacuje skok, vecji pa manjsi naklon.§Slojnice su uobicajena metoda da se prikaze oblik tla. Kao i na zemljovidima, mali razmak izmedu slojnica oznacava strminu, dok veliki razmak oznacava lagani pad.§Gradient lines are the most common methods to illustrate the ground structure. As on geographic maps narrow spacing indicates a steep and wide spacing a gentle slope.§Om de bodemstructuur aan te geven worden meestal overgangslijnen gebruikt. Net zoals op topografische kaarten, geven hoogtelijnen met een smalle tussenruimte een steilere helling aan, dan hoogtelijnen die verder van elkaar getekend zijn.§§§altitude_sealevel§1§Altitude above Sealevel§Höhenangaben (Seehöhe)§Altitude au-dessus du niveau de la mer§Quota s.l.m.§Nadmorska visina (m.n.m.)§Nadmorska visina (m.n.m)§Altitudini deasupra nivelului marii§Hoogte boven zeeniveau§§§This symbol has also been kept for reasons of consistence and designates the altitude above sea-level used in the map. It is highly recommended to write 1880 m. instead of just writing 1880. Generally maps are all to be done in SI units.§Dieses Symbol verbleibt in der Liste aus Konsistenzgründen. Es beschreibt die jeweilige Meereshöhe. Es wird empfohlen, die Höhe in Metern anzuschreiben und ein kleines "m" hintanzusetzen.§Ce symbole est maintenu pour des raisons de cohérence et désigne l'altitude au dessus du niveau de la mer utilisée dans les cartes topographiques. Il est fortement recommandé d'écrire "1880 m" au lieu de seulement "1880". En général les cartes sont toutes levées en unités du systcme international (SI).§Questo simbolo, mantenuto per ragioni di consistenza, definisce la quota sopra il livello del mare utilizzata nel rilievo, tipicamente in corrispondenza dell'ingresso. Viene calorosamente raccomandato di scrivere 1880 m invece del solo 1880, anche se i rilievi devono comunque utilizzare le unitr del Sistema Internazionale. §Znak ostaja zaradi tocnostnih razlogov. Oznacuje  nadmorsko visino dolocene tocke. Toplo se priporoca, da se ob visini, ki naj bo vedno podana v metrih, doda se "m.".§Ovaj simbol je zadrzan zbog konzistencije i oznacava nadmorsku visinu tocke na zemljovidu. Preporuca se da se uz visinu (u metrima) pise i mjerna jedinica ("m").§This symbol has also been kept for reasons of consistence and designates the altitude above sea-level used in the map. It is highly recommended to write 1880 m. instead of just writing 1880. Generally maps are all to be done in SI units.§Dit symbool wordt ook gebruikt op de topografische kaart en geeft de hoogte boven zee-niveau aan. Het wordt aanbevolen om 1880 m. te noteren i.p.v. alleen 1880. In het algemeen worden op kaarten SI-eenheden gebruikt.§§§difference_elevation§1§Difference in Elevation§Höhendifferenz§Altitude relative r l'entrée de la cavité§Differenza di quota§Visinska razlika§Visinska razlika§Altitudine relativa de la intrare§Hoogteverschil§§§in Relation to the entrance, as before§Diese Angaben beziehen sich auf das Eingangsniveau, wie zuvor§Comme auparavent.§invariato§Glede na vhod v jamo, kot do zdaj.§U odnosu na ulaz u objekt, kao i do sada.§in Relation to the entrance, as before§In relatie tot de ingang. Spreekt voor zich.§§§join_fault_bedding-plane§1§Joint - Fault - Bedding Plane - Inclined Joint§Kluft - Verwerfung - Schichtfuge - schräge Ebene§Fracture - faille - joint de strate - fracture inclince§Frattura-Faglia-Stratificazione§Razpoka - prelom - geoloska plast - nagnjena razpoka§Pukotina - Rasjed - Geoloski sloj - Nagnuta pukotina§Fractura-Falie-Fata de strat-Fractura înclinata§Breuk - Verschuiving - Laagvoeg§These symbols can be quite important for the understanding of the cave. Please use the symbols proposed here only when there's no appropriate set of symbols at the geological survey of your country. It is also recommended not to use any geological symbol unless one is totally sure about its nature. The arrow connecting two joint symbols is normally only used in the plan. It shows whether a cave crosses the same joint several times or whether it follows the joint itself.§Diese Symbole sind oftmals sehr wichtig für das Verständnis der Geologie der Höhle. Bitte verwendet die hier vorgeschlagenen Symbole nur, wenn es keine offiziellen geologischen Signaturen des geologischen Bundesamtes Eures Staates gibt. Es wird empfohlen geologischen Signaturen nur dann einzusetzen, wenn man sich über deren Natur im klaren ist. Der Pfeil, der zwei Kluftsymbole verbindet, wird normalerweise nur im Plan eingesetzt. Er zeigt, dass die beiden Kluftsymbole dieselbe (schräge) Kluft darstellen.§Ces symboles peuvent etre trcs importants pour la compréhension d'une cavité. Il est recommandé de n'utiliser les symboles proposés ici que s'il n'existe pas déja un symbole approprié utilisé dans les cartes géologiques de votre pays. Il est aussi recommandé de ne les utiliser que lorsque leur identification sur le terrain est certaine. Une flcche de connexion entre deux symboles de fracture n'est utilisée que sur le plan de la cavité. Cette flcche indique si la cavité traversé plusieurs fois la meme fracture ou si elle suit la fracture elle-meme.§Questi simboli possono essere piuttosto importanti per lo studio della grotta. Si raccomanda di non utilizzare questo tipo di simboli se non si c assolutamente confidenti nel loro utilizzo. Si raccomanda inoltre di utilizzare i simboli standard geologici nazionali. I simboli qui presentati sono a disposizione nel caso non esista uno standard geologico nazionale. La freccia che collega due simboli di frattura viene in genere usata solo in pianta. Essa mostra se la sezione longitudinale della grotta interseca diverse volte la frattura o e si sviluppa lungo di essa.§Ti znaki znajo biti zelo pomembni za razumevanje jame. Znake predlagane tu uporabljajte le, ce na geoloski karti vase dezele ni ustreznega nabora. Priporoca se, da geoloskih znakov ne uporabljamo, ce nismo popolnoma prepricani kaj pomenijo. Puscica, ki povezuje dva znaka za prelom se navadno uporablja le pri tlorisu, kjer pokaze, ali jama precka skozi isti prelom dvakrat ali pa mu kar sledi.§Ovi simboli mogu biti vrlo vazni za razumijevanje objekta. Preporuca se uporaba ovih simbola samo kad nema odgovarajucih geoloskih simbola na drzavnoj razini. Sa druge strane, ne preporuca se uporaba geoloskih simbola ukoliko nismo sigurni sto oni znace. Strelica koja spaja dva simbola pukotine koristi se na tlocrtu, a pokazuje da li objekt prelazi istu pukotinu vise puta, ili slijedi pukotinu.§These symbols can be quite important for the understanding of the cave. Please use the symbols proposed here only when there's no appropriate set of symbols at the geological survey of your country. It is also recommended not to use any geological symbol unless one is totally sure about its nature. The arrow connecting two joint symbols is normally only used in the plan. It shows whether a cave crosses the same joint several times or whether it follows the joint itself.§Deze symbolen kunnen erg belangrijk zijn om de grot te kunnen doorgronden. Gebruik de voorgestelde symbolen alleen als er in uw land geen bruikbare geologische symbolen-set is. Gebruik geen geologisch symbool als u niet absoluut zeker bent van de betekenis. De pijl die twee breuksymbolen verbindt, wordt normaal gebruikt in de plattegrond. Het laat zien of een grot dezelfde breuk meerdere keren kruist of de breuk volgt.§§§lake_water§0§Lake - Flowing Water§Seen und fliessende Gewässer§Lac-eau courante§Lago-Corso d'acqua§Jezero - vodni tok§Jezero - Vodeni tok§Lac - apa curgatoare§Meer - Stromend water§§§as before§wie zuvor§Comme auparavant.§invariato§Kot do zdaj.§Kao i do sada.§as before§Spreekt voor zich.§§§sump§0§Sump§Siphon§Siphon§Sifone§Sifon§Sifon§Sifon§sifon/watergevulde gang§§§as before. As an option it is possible to stop the crosshatching in order to draw the characteristics of the sump. This possibility, especially useful in longer sumps, is also shown.§wie zuvor. Als Option wird vorgeschlagen, die Kreuzschraffur zu unterbrechen, um die Charakteristiken des Siphons zu zeichnen. Diese Möglichkeit, vor allem in längeren Siphonen nützlich, wird hier gezeigt.§Comme auparavant. En option, il est possible d'interrompre les hachures croisées afin de dessiner les caractéristiques du siphon. Cette possibilité, particulicrement utile pour les siphons de grande longueur, est indiquée sur le schéma.§invariato. Come opzione, c possibile interrompere la campitura incrociata per mostrare dettagli del sifone. Questa possibilitr, utile soprattutto in sifoni lunghi, viene mostrata in figura.§Kot do zdaj. Vzporednice lahko tudi prekinemo, ce zelimo dorisati znacilnosti sifona. Ta moznost, ki je se posebej uporabna v daljsih sifonih, je prikazana na skici.§Kao i do sada. Opcionalno je moguce prekinuti srafiranje, da se nacrtaju karakteristike sifona. Ova mogucnost, korisna u dugim sifonima, prikazana je na slici.§as before. As an option it is possible to stop the crosshatching in order to draw the characteristics of the sump. This possibility, especially useful in longer sumps, is also shown.§Spreekt voor zich. Als optie bestaat de mogelijkheid om de kruisarcering te onderbreken om de karakteristieken van de sifon te tekenen. Deze mogelijkheid, speciaal handig bij langere watergangen, is hier ook afgebeeld.§§§cascade§0§Cascade - Waterfall§Wasserfall§Cascade / Chute d'eau§Cascata§Slap§Vodopad§missing§Cascade - Waterval§§§The symbol for waterfall is the same as the one for drop. To show flowing water one can draw an arrow indicating the flow before or at the side.§Das Symbol für Wasserfall ist das gleiche wie für eine Stufe oder Abbruchkante. Um das fliessende Gewässer anzuzeigen, soll ein (meist mäandrierender) Pfeil das Gerinne darstellen.§Le symbole pour une cascade est le meme que celui d'un escarpement. Pour montrer l'eau courante on peut dessiner une flcche indiquant le courant, devant ou sur le côté.§Il simbolo di cascata in Pianta c analogo a quello di salto. Per mostrare il flusso dell'acqua, c possibile disegnare una freccia che indica la direzione di flusso prima della cascata o a lato della stessa.§Znak za slap je enak kot znak za stopnjo. Za prikaz tekoce vode narisemo pred ali ob stopnji puscico.§Simbol za vodopad je isti kao i za skok. Da bi se pokazao tok vode, moguce je nacrtati strelice prije i/ili poslije skoka.§The symbol for waterfall is the same as the one for drop. To show flowing water one can draw an arrow indicating the flow before or at the side.§Het symbool voor een waterval is dezelfde als die van een put. Om stromend water af te beelden kan men een golvende pijl voor of naast de stroom tekenen.§§§spring_ponor§0§Spring - Sink§Quelle - Ponor§Source / perte§Sorgente - Inghiottitoio§Izvir - ponor§Izvor - Ponor§Izvor - Ponor-Pierdere de apa§Bron - verdwijnpunt§§§Springs or sinks which flow sideways in or out of a cave don't need a half circle to be characterised, whereas water inlets and outlets in the ground should be marked with a half-circle to distinguish them clearly from normal flowing water.<BR><BR>Symbols for temporary waters of all kinds have been omitted alltogether because of the following reasons: Hydrologically many water courses are also dry in dry times and are therefore also temporary. Adding to that, there have been many different symbols in the old symbol lists that would severely extend this list. One may add a note on temporary waters to the cave description.§Quellen und Ponore, die aus/in die Höhlenwände fliessen brauchen keine Halbkreise, solche am Höhlengrund sollten jedoch mit einem Halbkreis symbolisiert werden, um sie klar von normalen fliessendem Gewässer unterscheiden zu können.<BR><BR>Symbole für temporäre (perennierende) Gewässer wurden aus den folgenden Gründen gestrichen: Hydrologisch gesehen sind viele Gerinne zu Trockenzeiten vollständig trockengelegt und daher temporär. Es gab bisher eine verwirrende Vielfalt von verschiedenen Symbolen für diese temporären Gerinne. Man sollte diese eher in einer kurzen Notiz im Forschungsbericht bzw. in der Raumbeschreibung erwähnen.§Les sources et pertes venant/partant des parois de cavité de ne demandent pas r etre caractérisée par un demi-cercle, alors que les arrivées et les pertes d'eau au plancher doivent etre marquées d'un demi-cercle de façon r les différencier des cours d'eaux ordinaires.§Sorgenti e inghiottitio che si trovano a lato della cavitr non necessitano del semicerchio per essere evidenziate, mentre afflussi o deflussi d'acqua dal/nel suolo devono essere corredati dal semicerchio per distinguerli chiaramente dal semplice corso d'acqua.§Izvirom in ponorom, kjer voda v jamo prihaja ali odteka iz nje, na nacrtu ne risemo polkroga. Medtem ko moramo vodi, ki izgine ali se pojavi v tleh, dorisati polkrog, da jo s tem locimo od navadne tekoce vode.<BR><BR>Znake za obcasne vode kakrsnekoli vrste se opusca, ker je v suhi dobi lahko vsak vodni tok suh, znakov, ki so opisovali razlicne vrste obcasnih tokov, pa je bilo v starem seznamu prevec. Informacijo o obcasnih vodnih tokovih se doda v opis jame.§Izvorima ili ponorima, gdje voda u spilju dotice ili odtice, ne crtamo polukrug. Sa druge strane, mjesta na kojima se voda pojavljuje ili nestaje u kanalu (izvori ili ponori u kanalu) trebaju imati oznaku polukruga, da se jasno razlikuju od normalne tekuce vode.<BR><BR>Simboli za povremene tokove svih vrsta su izbaceni iz slijedecih razloga: hidroloski mnogi vodeni tokovi su suhi u susnim razdobljima, i stoga su povremeni. Dodantno, postoji puno simbola koji bi znatno prosirili ovu listu. Umjesto toga moze se dodati napomena o povremenom vodenom toku u opisu objekta.§Springs or sinks which flow sideways in or out of a cave don't need a half circle to be characterised, whereas water inlets and outlets in the ground should be marked with a half-circle to distinguish them clearly from normal flowing water.<BR><BR>Symbols for temporary waters of all kinds have been omitted alltogether because of the following reasons: Hydrologically many water courses are also dry in dry times and are therefore also temporary. Adding to that, there have been many different symbols in the old symbol lists that would severely extend this list. One may add a note on temporary waters to the cave description.§Bronnen of verdwijnpunten die zijdelings in of uit een grot stromen, hoeven niet met een halve cirkel gekarakteriseerd te worden, zoals water in- en uitlaten in de bodem wel gemarkeerd worden om hen te onderscheiden van stromend water. <BR><BR> Symbolen voor allerlei soorten tijdelijk water worden weggelaten om de volgende redenen: Hydrologische beddingen zijn in droge tijden ook droog en daarom tijdelijk. De vele oude symbolen zijn weggelaten om de lijst kort te houden. Men kan een aantekening over tijdelijke waterstromen toevoegen aan de grotbeschrijving.§§§water_inlet§0§Widespread Water Inlet - Seeping§Tropfwasser - Sickerwasser§Arrivée d'eau diffuse - Suintement d'eau dans un sédiment§Afflusso d'acqua diffuso -  Infiltrazione nel detrito§Razvejan pritok vode - ponikujoca voda§Razveden dotok vode - Sitasti ponor§Aport de apa difuz - Infiltratii§wijdverspreide waterinvoer - sijpels§§§There is no special symbol any more. It is needed to draw several ± parallel arrows indicating the flow. For seeping of a watercourse in sediment the semicircle is also used in the plan! In the longitudinal section the direction of the arrow can be bent towards the bottom to hint the seeping.§Es gibt kein Spezialsymbol mehr dafür. Es sollten mehrere +/- parallele Pfeile dafür gezeichnet werden. Für Sickerwasser sollte der Halbkreis auch im Plan verwendet werden! Im Längsschnitt kann der Pfeil absichtlich nach unten hin abgeknickt werden, um das Versickern verstärkt anzudeuten.§Il n'y a plus de symbole particulier. Il suffit de dessiner quelques flcches plus ou moins parallcles indiquant l'arrivée d'eau. - Suintement d'eau dans un sédiment: Ici, le demi-cercle est aussi utilisé dans le plan! Dans la coupe longitudinale, la direction de la flcche peut etre courbée vers le bas pour indiquer le suintement. Les symboles pour les écoulements d'eau temporaires ont tous été supprimés pour les raisons suivantes : hydrologiquement parlant, beaucoup de cours d'eau sont aussi r sec en période de sécheresse et sont donc aussi temporaires. De plus, il y avait trop de symboles différents dans l'ancienne liste ce qui aurait trop chargé la présente liste. Il est préférable de signaler ces phénomcnes dans la description écrite de la cavité.§<B>Afflusso d'acqua diffuso:</B> Il simbolo apposito c stato abolito. C sufficiente disegnare alcune frecce sub-parallele ad indicare il flusso.<P><B>Infiltrazione nel detrito:</B> In questo caso il semicerchio viene usato anche nella pianta. In sezione longitudinale, la direzione della freccia pun puntare verso il basso ad indicare l'assorbimento. <P><I>La distinzione fra corpi idrici perenni e temporanei viene abolita. Questa scelta c dovuta al fatto che la maggior parte dei corsi d'acqua sono asciutti in periodi di siccitr, per cui sono anch'essi temporanei. Inoltre, si c scelto di mantenere limitato il numero di simboli presenti in lista, a favore di una maggiore semplicitr. C piu opportuno aggiungere una nota sul regime idrico del corso d'acqua nella descrizione della cavitr</I>§Ni vec posebega znaka, ki bi oznaceval razvejan pritok vode. Narise se vec bolj  ali manj vzporednih puscic, ki kazejo tok. Pri ponikanju vode v talne sedimenta se na tlorisu uporablja polkrog. Pri stranskem risu pa se puscico usmeri v tla in s tem nakaze ponikanje.§Ne postoji vise poseban simbol za rezvedeni dotok vode. Umjesto toga crtaju se vise ili manje paralelne strelice koje oznacavaju tok vode.<BR><BR>Za poniranje vode u sedimente na tlu rabi se polukrug na tlocrtu. U ispruzenom profilu strelica se usmjeri prema tlu i tako se oznacava curenje kroz sediment.§There is no special symbol any more. It is needed to draw several ± parallel arrows indicating the flow. For seeping of a watercourse in sediment the semicircle is also used in the plan! In the longitudinal section the direction of the arrow can be bent towards the bottom to hint the seeping.§Er is geen speciaal symbool meer. Als het nodig is teken dan een aantal ongeveer parallelle pijltjes om de stroom aan te geven. Waar water wegsijpelt in zand (sediment) tekenen we de halve cirkel ook in de plattegrond. In de langsdoorsnede kunnen we de golvende pijl naar onderen laten wijzen om een hint te geven van het wegsijpelen.§§§scallop_flutes§0§Scallops, Flutes in General, Direction of Paleoflow§Kolke - Fliessfacetten - Paläofliessrichtung§Coupoles d'érosion - marmites - courant d'ccoulement fossile§Scallops - Scanellature in general - Direzione del paleoflusso§Kotlice - zlebici (fasete) - smer starega toka.§Vrtlozni lonci - Zljebici (fasete) - Smjer fosilnog toka§Cupole de eroziune - marmite - curent de apa fosil§Erosie koepels, kolkgaten,  richting van de paleo-stroom§§§Flow Casts (Scallops): as before.<BR><BR>Flute: The differentiation between erosional and corrosion flutes has been omitted, because, especially with flutes on lateral walls, they cannot always be identified correctly. The new symbol can be rotated; if the semicircle is on top, it shows a flute on the ceiling, etc.<BR><BR>Paleoflow: This very useful symbol is not only used with scallops, but also with ripple marks, imbrications and other features. In addition it might be used in lava caves to show the flow direction of the lava.§Fliessfacetten: wie zuvor<BR><BR>Paläoflussrichtung: Dieses sehr brauchbare Symbol wird nicht nur im Zusammenhang mit Fliessfacetten, sondern auch zusammen mit Wirbeln etc. verwendet. Zusätzlich kann es in Lavahöhlen verwendet werden, um die Fliessrichtung der Lava anzuzeigen.<BR><BR>Kolke: Die Unterscheidung zwischen Erosions- und Korrosionskolken wurde weggelassen, da eine korrekte Identifizierung der Genese eines Kolkes oft sehr schwierig ist. Das neue Symbol kann rotiert werden. Wenn der Halbkreis oben ist, zeigt es einen Deckenkolk, ist der Halbkreis unten einen Kolk am Boden etc.§Coupoles d'érosion: comme auparavant<BR><BR>Courant d'écoulement fossile: Ce symbole trcs utile s'utilise non seulement avec les coupoles d'érosion, mais aussi avec les vagues de sable et les imbrications et autres marques caractéristiques. De plus, il peut etre utilisé dans les tubes de lave pour indiquer la direction du flot de lave.<BR><BR>Marmites: La différentiation entre marmites de corrosion et d'érosion a été supprimée, car elle est difficile r identifier spécialement sur les parois. Le nouveau symbole peut etre tourné dans le sens voulu si le demi-cercle est au-dessus, il indique une marmite au plafond, etc.§<B>Scallops:</B> Il simbolo c di facile comprensione e rimane immutato. Viene omessa la freccia di flusso.<P><B>Paleoflusso:</B> Questo nuovo simbolo pun essere usato non solo per gli scallop, ma anche per i ripple mark, le embricature e altre morfologie similari. Inoltre pun essere utile nelle grotte laviche, per indicare la direzione di flusso della lava.<P><B>Scanellature (Flutes):</B> La distinzione fra scanellature da erosione o da corrosione viene abolita perché la distinzione pun essere molto difficile, specialmente per le scanellature sulle pareti. Il simbolo pun essere ruotato. Se il semicerchio c in alto, identifica una scanellatura a soffitto, e cose via.§Kotlice: kot do zdaj. <BR><BR> fasete in zlebici: opustilo se je razlikovanje med erozijskimi in korozijskimi zlebici, saj je razlikovanje med obojimi se posebej na stranskih stenah precej tezavno. Novi znak se lahko obraca. Ce je polkrog zgoraj, oznacuje zlebic na stropu. <BR><BR> Smer starega toka (paleotoka): ta zelo uporaben znak se da uporabiti tudi pri drugih znakih nekdanjega vodnega toka, ne le pri fasetah. Lahko pa se uporabi tudi v vulkanskih jamah za prikaz nekdanjega toka lave.§Vrtlozni lonci: Kao i do sada.<BR><BR>Fasete: Razlika izmedu erozijskih i korozijskih fasete je izostavljena, jer je njihovo razlikovanje prlilicno tesko, pogotovo sa fasetama na bocnim stjenama. Ovaj simbol moze se rotirati, tako da polukrug na vrhu oznacava fasetu na stropu i sl.<BR><BR>Smjer fosilnog toka (paleotoka): Ovaj vrlo koristan simbol koristi se i uz druge znakove vodenog toka (npr. tragovi valova, ljuskice), a ne samo uz vrtlozne lonce. U vulkanskim spiljama moze se koristiti za prikaz nekadasnjeg toka lave.§Flow Casts (Scallops): as before.<BR><BR>Flute: The differentiation between erosional and corrosion flutes has been omitted, because, especially with flutes on lateral walls, they cannot always be identified correctly. The new symbol can be rotated; if the semicircle is on top, it shows a flute on the ceiling, etc.<BR><BR>Paleoflow: This very useful symbol is not only used with scallops, but also with ripple marks, imbrications and other features. In addition it might be used in lava caves to show the flow direction of the lava.§Erosie koepels/scallops (in plafond): spreekt voor zich.<BR><BR>Kolkgaten: het verschil tussen erosie- en corrosiegaten is onduidelijk omdat vooral met gaten in wanden, het niet altijd mogelijk is dit juist te determineren. Het nieuwe symbool kan gedraaid worden; als de halve cirkel boven zit, laat het een kolkgat in het plafond zien.<BR><BR>Paleo-stroom; Dit nuttige symbool wordt niet alleen gebruikt als er kolkgaten in het spel zijn maar ook met rimpel-groeven, imbrikaties en andere features. In lavagrotten kan het gebruikt worden om de lavastroom mee aan te geven.§§§air_draught_ice§0§Air draught - Ice/Snow/Firn§Luftzug - Eis/Schnee/Firn§Courant d'air - Glace/neige/givre§Corrente d'aria - Ghiaccio - Neve - Firn§Prepih - led/sneg/srez§Propuh - Led/Snijeg/Inje§Curent de aer - Gheata-zapada-firn§luchtstroom - Ijs-Sneeuw-firn§§§Air draught: This is a well known symbol. It should always include the date of measurement. The symbol now uses always two feathers! The date of measurement should be written in the standard dd-mm-yyyy format!<BR><BR>Ice/Snow/Firn: The old star symbol used for snow hasn´t been satisfactory for quite some time as it is very time consuming to draw and the ground structure cannot be shown. Added to this, it can easily be mistaken for the crystal symbol. The old symbol for ice is confusingly similar to true gradient lines. Taking all this into consideration we agreed on the following solution: Snow is transformed to firn and subsequently to ice. By morphology and composition all three substances are the same, therefore it should be represented by the same symbol. The one that has been chosen is easy to draw, shows the ground structure and cannot be mixed up.§Luftzug: Das Symbol hat immer zwei Federn. Es sollte unbedingt das Aufnahmedatum (tt-mm-jjjj) dabeistehen.<BR><BR>Eis/Schnee/Firn: Das alte Sternsymbol, das bisher für Schnee verwendet wurde, ist einerseits nicht sehr befriedigend, andererseits zeitraubend beim Zeichnen. Ausserdem kann damit die Oberflächenstruktur schlecht gezeigt werden. Zusätzlich kann das Sternsymbol leicht mit der Signatur für Kristalle verwechselt werden. Das alte Symbol für Eis ist zur Verwechslung ähnlich mit den Gefällelinien. Wir entschieden uns für die folgende Lösung: Schnee wird zu Firn und schliesslich zu Eis. Von der Morphologie und Zusammensetzung sind alle drei Zusammensetzungen sehr ähnlich und können deshalb ohne weiteres mit dem gleichen Symbol gezeichnet werden. Das neu gewählte Symbol ist leicht zu zeichnen, zeigt die Oberflächenstruktur und die Verwechslungsgefahr ist gering.§Courant d'air: C'est un symbole trcs courant, qui doit toujours comporter la date d'observation. Le symbole utilise maintenant toujours deux chevrons! La date s'écrit au format standard jj-mm-aaaa.<BR><BR>Glace / neige / givre: L'ancien symbole pour la neige (étoile pleine) n'est plus satisfaisant, car trop long r dessiner et ne permettant pas de représenter la structure du sol. il pouvait aussi donner lieu r confusion avec le symbole des cristaux. L'ancien symbole de la glace pouvait etre confondu avec des lignes de gradient. Finalement la solution suivante a été adoptée : la neige se transformant en neige glacée puis en glace, ces trois substances sont identiques par leur morphologie et leur composition. Elles doivent donc etre représentées par le meme symbole. Le symbole choisi est simple r dessiner, permet de représenter la structure du sol et ne prete pas r confusion. La date d'observation doit etre écrite au format standard jj-mm-aaaa!§<B>Corrente d'aria:</B> Si tratta di un simbolo ben noto, che ora viene rappresentato sempre con due trattini. La data di rilevazione va sempre inclusa, nel formato standard gg-mm-aaaa.<P><B>Ghiaccio / Neve / Firn:</B> Il precedente simbolo utilizzato per rappresentare la neve (una stellina a sei punte) c piuttosto complesso da disegnare e non permette di rappresentare la struttura del suolo. Analogamente, il precedente simbolo per il ghiaccio poteva essere confuso con quello di curva di livello. Dato che neve, firn e ghiaccio sono una l'evoluzione dell'altra, si c convenuto di rappresentarle tutte con un nuovo simbolo unico, che c semplice da disegnare, permette di rappresentare la struttura del suolo e non pun essere confuso con altri. Data la variabilitr dei depositi nevosi o glaciali, c fondamentale aggiungere la data di osservazione, che deve essere espressa nel formato standard gg-mm-aaaa.§Prepih: To je dobro znan znak. Ob njem mora vedno biti napisan datum merjenja prepiha. Znak ima sedaj na repu vedno dve vzporedni crtici. Datum mora biti podan v standardni obliki dd-mm-llll. <BR><BR> Led, sneg, srez: star znak za sneg - zvezdica - ni bil zadovoljiv, ker ga je zamudno risati, in, ker se z njim ne da  prikazati oblike tal. Poleg tega ga ni bilo tezko zamesati z znakom za kristale. Star znak za led je prepodoben naklonskim crtam. Upostevajoc to smo se dogovorili za naslednjo resitev: sneg se spreminja v srez in nadalje v led. Morfolosko in po sestavi so vse tri snovi enake, torej bi morale biti oznacene z istim znakom. Nov znak je enostaven za narisati, prikazuje obliko tal in se ga ne da zamesati.§Propuh: Dobro znan simbol. Uvijek treba ukljucivati i datum mjerenja (u standardnom DD.MM.GGGG obliku). Simbol (strelica) sada ima dva repa.<BR><BR>Led/Snijeg/Inje: Stari simbol za snijeg (zvjezdica) nije zadovoljavajuci jer oduzima puno vremena za crtanje te se ne moze prikazati oblik tla. Dodatno, lako se moze zamijeniti sa simbolom za kristale. Stari simbol za led je poprilicno slican slojnicama. Uzimajuci sve ovo u obzir, slozeno je slijedece rjesenje: snijeg se transformira u inje pa u led. Po morfologiji i sastavu, sve tri tvari su jednake, pa bi trebale biti predstavljene istim simbolom. Novi simbol je lak za crtanje, pokazuje strukturu tla i ne moze ga se zamijeniti.§Air draught: This is a well known symbol. It should always include the date of measurement. The symbol now uses always two feathers! The date of measurement should be written in the standard dd-mm-yyyy format!<BR><BR>Ice/Snow/Firn: The old star symbol used for snow hasn´t been satisfactory for quite some time as it is very time consuming to draw and the ground structure cannot be shown. Added to this, it can easily be mistaken for the crystal symbol. The old symbol for ice is confusingly similar to true gradient lines. Taking all this into consideration we agreed on the following solution: Snow is transformed to firn and subsequently to ice. By morphology and composition all three substances are the same, therefore it should be represented by the same symbol. The one that has been chosen is easy to draw, shows the ground structure and cannot be mixed up.§Luchtstroom: Dit is een bekend symbool. Het moet vergezeld gaan van de meetdatum. Het symbool heeft altijd twee veertjes. De datum moet worden genoteerd in dd-mm-jjjj format. <BR><BR> IJS/Sneeuw/Firn; Het oude ster-symbool voldeed niet. Het koste veel tijd om het te tekenenen en de bodemstructuur kan niet worden afgebeeld. Het kan ook gemakkelijk worden verward met het kristal-symbool. Het oude IJS-symbool kan gemakkelijk worden verward met de “echte” overgangslijnen. Dit alles in overweging genomen is er voor de volgende oplossing gekozen: Sneeuw gaat over in firn dat weer overgaat in IJS. Door morfologie en compositie zijn ze alle drie van dezelfde substantie en zouden afgebeeld moeten worden met hetzelfde symbool. Het gekozen symbool is gemakkelijk te tekenen, laat de bodemstructuur zien en kan niet worden verwisseld voor een ander symbool.§stalagmites§0§Stalagmites§Stalagmiten§Stalagmites§Stalagmiti§Stalagmiti§Stalagmiti§Stalagmite§Stalagmieten§§§as before§wie zuvor§Comme auparavant.§invariato. C stata abolita la rappresentazione in pianta come un cerchietto pieno.§Kot do zdaj.§Kao i do sada.§as before§Spreekt voor zich.§§§stalactites§0§Stalactites§Stalaktiten§Stalactites§Stalattiti§Stalaktiti§Stalaktiti§Stalactite§Stalactieten§§§as before§wie zuvor§Comme auparavant.§invariato. C stata abolita la rappresentazione in pianta come un cerchietto vuoto.§Kot do zdaj.§Kao i do sada.§as before§Spreekt voor zich.§§§sinter-curtains_pillars§0§Sinter Curtains - Pillars§Sintervorhänge - Tropfsteinsäulen§Draperies stalagmitiques - Piliers stalagmitiques§Cortina di concrezione - Colonna§Sigova zavesa - steber§Zavjese od sigovine - Stupovi§Draperii stalagmitice - coloane-pilieri stalagmitici§Gordijnen - Pilaren§§§Calcite Curtains: The presented solution is not easily understood at first sight but seems to be the best (alternatively you draw the curtains into your map).<BR><BR>Calcite pillars: as before§Sintervorhänge: Die gezeigte Lösung ist im ersten Blick nicht allzu verständlich, aber schien uns als die beste Lösung.<BR><BR>Tropfsteinsäulen: wie zuvor§Draperies stalagmitiques: La solution proposée n'est pas facile r comprendre r premicre vue, mais semble la meilleure (sauf si vous dessinez les draperies sur votre topographie). - Piliers stalagmitiques: Comme auparavant.§<B>Cortina di concrezione:</B> La soluzione presentata non c di immediata comprensione ma c stata adottata come evoluzione del simbolo precedente, in mancanza di soluzioni migliori. C inoltre possibile dare una rappresentazione pseudo-realistica.<P><B>Colonna:</B> invariato. C stata abolita la rappresentazione in pianta come un cerchietto.§Zavese: predstavljena resitev na prvi pogled ni najbolj razumljiva, vendar boljsih ni. <BR><BR> Steber: kot do zdaj.§Zavjese od sigovine: Prikazano rjesenje nije razumlnjivo na prvi pogled, ali boljih nema. <BR><BR>Stupovi: Kao i do sada.§Calcite Curtains: The presented solution is not easily understood at first sight but seems to be the best (alternatively you draw the curtains into your map).<BR><BR>Calcite pillars: as before§Gordijnen: Het gekozen symbool wordt niet gemakkelijk herkend, maar lijkt het beste (als alternatief kun je gordijnen op je kaart tekenen). <BR><BR>Pilaren: spreekt voor zich.§§§helictites_spaghetti_crystals§0§Helictites - Soda Straws - Crystals§Excentriques - Spaghetti - Kristalle§Excentriques/Helictites - Spaghettis - Cristaux§Concrezione eccentrica - Spaghetti - Cristalli§Heliktiti - spageti (cevcice) - kristali§Heliktiti - Spageti - Kristali§Excentrite-Helictite - macaroane - cristale§excentrieken - macaronies - kristallen§§§Helictites: This symbol is as eccentric as the formation itself and is therefore easily understood.<BR><BR>Soda Straws: This symbol doesn´t need any further explanations.<BR><BR>Crystals: For reasons of international understanding the letters identifying the minerals should be avoided, first because correct mineral identification is often not as easy as it may seem, and second because a C for calcite is an K in German and a # in Chinese. In general we do not recommend the use of letters as symbols on the actual map. The resulting babylonic confusion can be lethal for the understanding.§Excentriques: Das Symbol ist exzentrisch wie die Formation selbst und daher leicht verständlich.<BR><BR>Spaghetti: braucht keine weiteren Erklärungen.<BR><BR>Kristalle: Wegen der internationalen Verständlichkeit sollten Buchstaben, die die Mineralien identifizieren, eher weggelassen werden, da erstens die korrekte Identifizierung häufig schwierig ist und zweitens ein "C" für Calcite in Englisch ein "K" auf Deutsch ist und ein "#" in Chinesisch. Generell empfehlen wir, von der Verwendung von einzelnen Buchstaben als Symbole abzusehen, da diese nicht standardisiert sind und eher einer babylonischen Sprachenverwirrung beitragen.§Excentriques / Helictites: Ce symbole est d'autant plus excentrique que la formation réelle l'est, et est donc facilement interprétable.<BR><BR>Spaghettis: Pas besoin d'explications supplémentaires.<BR><BR>Cristaux: Pour des raisons de compréhension internationale, les lettres identifiant les minéraux doivent etre évitées, d'abord parce que l'identification précise des minéraux n'est pas aussi facile qu'il y parait, et ensuite parce que l'abréviation de calcite est K en allemand, C en anglais et français et # en chinois. De façon générale, nous ne recommandons pas l'utilisation de lettres comme symboles sur les topographies, la confusion générée pouvant etre catastrophique pour la compréhension internationale.§<B>Concrezione eccentrica:</B> Questo simbolo c tanto eccentrico quanto la morfologia che vuole rappresentare, per cui dovrebbe essere di facile comprensione.<P><B>Spaghetti:</B> Questo simbolo non richiede ulteriori spiegazioni.<P><B>Cristalli:</B> Per ragioni di comprensione sovranazionale, c opportuno evitare l'utilizzo di lettere ad identificare il tipo di minerale. Il simbolo utilizzato veniva in passato impiegato per rappresentare la neve.§Heliktiti: Znak naj bi bil toliko ekscentricen kot je heliktit, ki ga oznacuje, in je torej dobro prepoznaven. <BR><BR> Spageti: znak ne potrebuje dodatne razlage. <BR><BR> Kristali: zaradi zelje po vecji razumljivosti nacrta, naj bi se izogibali crkam, ki oznacujejo vrsto minerala. Natancno ugotavljanje vrste minerala pogosto ni tako lahko, kot se zdi, pa tudi crke, ki oznacujejo recimo kalcit, se med narodi in jeziki razlikujejo.  §Heliktiti: Ovaj simbol je ekscentrican kao i sama formacija i stoga lako prepoznatljiv.<BR><BR>Spageti: Simbol ne treba posebna objasnjenja.<BR><BR>Kristali: Zbog zelje za cim razumljivijim nacrtom, trebalo bi izbjegavati slova za oznake minerala, jer tocno identificiranje minerala cesto nije jednostavno, a i slova za istu vrstu minerala se razlikuju od drzave do drzave.§Helictites: This symbol is as eccentric as the formation itself and is therefore easily understood.<BR><BR>Soda Straws: This symbol doesn´t need any further explanations.<BR><BR>Crystals: For reasons of international understanding the letters identifying the minerals should be avoided, first because correct mineral identification is often not as easy as it may seem, and second because a C for calcite is an K in German and a # in Chinese. In general we do not recommend the use of letters as symbols on the actual map. The resulting babylonic confusion can be lethal for the understanding.§Excentrieken: Dit symbool is net zo excentriek als de formaties zelf en wordt daarom gemakkelijk herkend. <BR><BR>macaronies: spreekt voor zich.<BR><BR>Kristallen: Om internationaal begrepen te worden moeten de letters van de kristal-mineralen weggelaten worden. Ten eerste omdat mineralen identificatie niet zo gemakkelijk is als dat het lijkt en ten tweede omdat een C voor Calciet in het Duits een K is en in het chinees een #. In het algemeen is het niet raadzaam om letters als symbool in de kaart op te nemen. De resulterende Babylonische spraakverwarring kan dodelijk zijn voor het begrip.§§§sinter_pools§0§Sinter Pools§Sinterbecken§Gours§Grandi vasche - Vaschette di concrezione§Sigove ponvice§Zasigane kaskade§Gururi§Sinter-bekkens§§§as before§wie zuvor§Comme auparavant.§invariato.§Kot do zdaj.§Kao i do sada.§as before§spreekt voor zich.§§§floorsinter_wallsinter_moonmilk§0§Flowstone - Wall Calcite - Moonmilk§Bodensinter - Wandsinter - Mondmilch (Bergmilch)§Concrétionnement au sol - Concrétionnement sur les parois - Mondmilch§Colata a pavimento - Colata parietale - Latte di Monte§Zasigano pobocje - zasigana stena - jamsko mleko§Zasigano tlo - Zasigana stijena - Spiljsko mlijeko§Planseu concretionat - concretiuni parietale - montmilch§Bodemdruipsteen - afzettingen op de wand - bergmelk§§§Flowstone: Often this or a similar symbol is also used for clay (see there).<BR><BR>Wall Calcite: as before<BR><BR>Moonmilk: To avoid mistaking this symbol for the guano symbol an additional bow has been added to the usual m.§Bodensinter: Dieses Symbol wird auch oft für Lehm verwendet (siehe dort).<BR>Wandsinter: wie zuvor<BR>Mondmilch (Bergmilch): Um Verwechslungen mit dem Guano-Symbol zu vermeiden, wurde hier zum üblichen (m) noch ein dritter Bogen hinzugefügt.§Concrétionnement au sol: Souvent utilisé pour représenter l'argile (voir ci-dessous).<BR><BR>Concrétionnement sur les parois: Comme auparavant.<BR><BR>Mondmilch: Pour éviter toute confusion avec le symbole utilisé pour le guano, une jambe supplémentaire a été rajoutée au "m" habituel.§<B>Colata di concrezione a pavimento:</B> Dal momento che le colate di concrezione a pavimento sono piuttosto frequenti, era opportuno introdurre un simbolo specifico. I trattini orizzontali paralleli sono una buona soluzione, dal momento che permettono anche di rappresentare la struttura del suolo. Purtroppo in passato questo simbolo veniva utilizzato per rappresentare l'argilla, e cin pun ingenerare confusione.<P><B>Colata parietale / Concrezionamento in genere:</B> invariato.<P><B>Latte di monte:</B> Per evitare di confondere questo simbolo con quello di "guano", c stato aggiunto un terzo archetto al simbolo precedentemente usato (una M).§Sigovo pobocje: Pogosto je ta ali podoben znak uporabljan tudi za glino oz. blato.<BR><BR> Zasigana stena: kot do sedaj. <BR><BR> Jamsko mleko: da se ta znak ne bi zamenjevalo z znakom za guano, je bil k obicajnemu 'm' dodan tretji lok. §Zasigano tlo: Cesto se ovaj ili slican simbol upotrebljava za glinu.<BR><BR>Zasigana stijena: Kao i do sada.<BR><BR>Spiljsko mlijeko: Da se ne bi ovaj simbol mijesao sa simbolom za guano, dodan je treci luk na uobicajeno m.§Flowstone: Often this or a similar symbol is also used for clay (see there).<BR><BR>Wall Calcite: as before<BR><BR>Moonmilk: To avoid mistaking this symbol for the guano symbol an additional bow has been added to the usual m.§Druipsteen: vaak wordt hetzelfde symbool gebruikt voor klei (zie daar). <BR><BR>Bergmelk/moonmilk: Om vergissing te voorkomen met het guano-symbool worden drie boogjes getekend i.p.v. de twee (vogeltje/vleermuis) boogjes.§§§north_arrow_geographic_cartesic§1§North Arrow Geographic and Cartesic§Geographisch und Kartesisch Nord (Gitternord)§Nord géographique et cartographique§Nord Geografico et Cartesiano§Geografski sever - Kartezijski sever§Zemljopisni (geografski) i Kartezijski sjever§Directia nord - geografic and cartigrafic§Noord pijl Geografisch en Cartesisch§§§On several maps, information on declination is missing or is incomplete, which makes the calculation of geographic north almost impossible. Beside the normal North arrow one must specify whether one relates to geographic, magnetic, or cartographers north. If one is relating to magnetic north the date of measurement must be mentioned. Both versions shown are equivalent.§Auf vielen Plänen fehlen die Angaben zur Deklination oder sind unvollständig, was eine Berechnung von Geographisch Nord vielfach unmöglich macht. Neben dem üblichen Nordpfeil muss man angeben, ob man sich auf Geographisch Nord, Magnetisch Nord oder Gitternord bezieht. Wenn man sich auf Magnetisch Nord bezieht, muss das Vermessungsdatum notiert werden. Für Geographisch Nord sind die Versionen mit oder ohne Stern äquivalent.§Sur de nombreuses cartes, l'information sur la déclinaison n'est pas disponible ou incomplcte, ne permettant pas de calculer le Nord géographique. A côté de la flcche représentant le Nord, il est impératif de préciser si elle réfcre au Nord magnétique, géographique ou celui des cartographes. En cas de Nord magnétique, il est impératif de préciser la date de mesure. Les deux possibilités dessiniées sont équivalent.§Su diverse carte, le informazioni sulla declinazione magnetica sono mancanti o incomplete, rendendo impossibile il calcolo del Nord geografico. In aggiunta alla classica direzione del Nord, c necessario specificare sui rilievi se ci si riferisce al Nord geografico, magnetico o cartesiano. Se ci si riferisce al Nord magnetico, c necessario specificare la data del rilevamento. Il Nord geografico pun essere rappresentato sia come una freccia con una semplice N, o come una freccia con una N ed una stellina.§Na stevilnih nacrtih ni podatka o azimutu oziroma je le ta pomankljiv, kar naredi izracun geografskega severa skoraj nemogoc. Poleg obicajne puscice, ki kaze sever, moramo oznaciti ali imamo v mislih geografski, magnetni ali kartezijski sever. Ce se naslanjamo na magnetni sever, moramo pripisati se datum merjenja. Oba mozna nacina prikaza geografskega severa sta prikazana.§Na nekim zemljovidima, nedostaje ili je nepotpun podatak o deklinaciji, sto onemogucava izracun zemljopisnog sjevera. Osim normalne strelice na koja oznacava sjever, mora se oznaciti da li se odnosi na zemljopisni, magnetski ili kartografski (kartezijski) sjever. Ako se odnosi na magnetski sjever, datum mjerenja mora biti spomenut. Oba moguca simbola su prikazana.§On several maps, information on declination is missing or is incomplete, which makes the calculation of geographic north almost impossible. Beside the normal North arrow one must specify whether one relates to geographic, magnetic, or cartographers north. If one is relating to magnetic north the date of measurement must be mentioned. Both versions shown are equivalent.§Op verschillende kaarten mist de informatie over declinatie of is incompleet. Dit maakt de berekening van het geografische noorden bijna onmogelijk. Behalve de normale noordpijl moet men de relatie tussen het geografische, magnetische en kaartnoorden aangeven. Als men refereert aan het magnetische noorden moet men ook de datum van de meting vermelden. De twee getoonde pijlen zijn gelijkwaardig.§§§north_arrow_magnetic§1§North Arrow Magnetic§Magnetisch Nord§Nord magnétique§Nord Magnetico§Magnetni sever§Magnetski sjever§Directia nord magnetic§Noordpijl Magnetisch Noorden§§§On several maps, information on declination is missing or is incomplete, which makes the calculation of geographic north almost impossible. Beside the normal North arrow one must specify whether one relates to geographic, magnetic, or cartographers north. If one is relating to magnetic north the date of measurement must be mentioned.§Auf vielen Plänen fehlen die Angaben zur Deklination oder sind unvollständig, was eine Berechnung von Geographisch Nord vielfach unmöglich macht. Neben dem üblichen Nordpfeil muss man angeben, ob man sich auf Geographisch Nord, Magnetisch Nord oder Gitternord bezieht. Wenn man sich auf Magnetisch Nord bezieht, muss das Vermessungsdatum notiert werden. Für Geographisch Nord sind die Versionen mit oder ohne Stern äquivalent.§Sur de nombreuses cartes, l'information sur la déclinaison n'est pas disponible ou incomplcte, ne permettant pas de calculer le Nord géographique. A côté de la flcche représentant le Nord, il est impératif de préciser si elle réfcre au Nord magnétique, géographique ou celui des cartographes. En cas de Nord magnétique, il est impératif de préciser la date de mesure.§Su diverse carte, le informazioni sulla declinazione magnetica sono mancanti o incomplete, rendendo impossibile il calcolo del Nord geografico. In aggiunta alla classica direzione del Nord, c necessario specificare sui rilievi se ci si riferisce al Nord geografico, magnetico o cartesiano. Se ci si riferisce al Nord magnetico, c necessario specificare la data del rilevamento. Il Nord geografico pun essere rappresentato sia come una freccia con una semplice N, o come una freccia con una N ed una stellina.§Na stevilnih nacrtih ni podatka o azimutu oziroma je le ta pomankljiv, kar naredi izracun geografskega severa skoraj nemogoc. Poleg obicajne puscice, ki kaze sever, moramo oznaciti ali imamo v mislih geografski, magnetni ali kartezijski sever. Ce se naslanjamo na magnetni sever, moramo pripisati se datum merjenja. Oba mozna nacina prikaza geografskega severa sta prikazana.§Na nekim zemljovidima, nedostaje ili je nepotpun podatak o deklinaciji, sto onemogucava izracun zemljopisnog sjevera. Osim normalne strelice na koja oznacava sjever, mora se oznaciti da li se odnosi na zemljopisni, magnetski ili kartografski (kartezijski) sjever. Ako se odnosi na magnetski sjever, datum mjerenja mora biti spomenut.§On several maps, information on declination is missing or is incomplete, which makes the calculation of geographic north almost impossible. Beside the normal North arrow one must specify whether one relates to geographic, magnetic, or cartographers north. If one is relating to magnetic north the date of measurement must be mentioned.§Op verschillende kaarten mist de informatie over declinatie of is incompleet. Dit maakt de berekening van het geografische noorden bijna onmogelijk. Behalve de normale noordpijl moet men de relatie tussen het geografische, magnetische en kaartnoorden aangeven. Als men refereert aan het magnetische noorden moet men ook de datum van de meting vermelden. De twee getoonde pijlen zijn gelijkwaardig.§§§block_debris§0§Blocks - Debris§Blockwerk, Geröll§Blocs, débris§Massi - Detriti a spigoli vivi§Bloki - grusc§Blokovi - Krslje§Blocuri - prabusiri§Blokken - rol-steentjes§§§as before. The size can be modelled on the reality.§wie zuvor. Die Grösse kann sich bei grösserem Blockwerk an der Realität orientieren.§Comme auparavant. La taille des symboles peut etre proportionnée r la réalité.§invariato. La grafica pun essere rappresentativa delle dimensioni reali.§Kot do zdaj. Velikost naj bi prikazovala dejansko stanje.§Kao i do sada. Blokovi (velicina i oblik) se modeliraju prema stvarnima.§as before. The size can be modelled on the reality.§Spreekt voor zich. Het formaat kan gemodelleerd worden naar de werkelijkheid.§§§pebbles§0§Pebbles§Kiesel§Cailloux§Ciottoli - Detriti a spigoli arrotondati§Prodniki§Sljunak§Pietris§Kiezels§§§as before. The size can be modelled on the reality.§wie zuvor. Die Korngrösse ist abhängig von der Realität.§Comme auparavant. La taille des symboles peut etre proportionnée r la réalité.§invariato. La grafica pun essere rappresentativa delle dimensioni reali.§Kot do zdaj. Velikost naj bi prikazovala dejansko stanje.§Kao i do sada. Velicina se modelira prema stvarnosti.§as before. The size can be modelled on the reality.§Spreekt voor zich. Het formaat kan gemodelleerd worden naar de werkelijkheid.§§§clastic_sediments§0§Clastic sediments: Sand - Silt - Clay - Humus§Klastische Sedimente: Sand - Schlamm - Lehm - Erde§Sédiments clastiques : Sable, limon, argile et humus§Sedimento fine: Sabbia - Limo - Argilla - Humus§Klasticni sedimenti: Pesek - mulj - glina (blato) - prst§Klasticni sedimenti: Pijesak - Mulj - Glina - Humus§§§Sediment clastic - nisip, mâl, argila, humus§Sedimenten: Zand - Zilt - Klei/Leem - Humus§With the exception of humus this group is a sediment whose grain size and therefore names depend on the velocity of current of the carrying water. In flowing water sand is deposited whereas in standing water clay is deposited. In contrast to this the flowstone (see there), which is a chemical precipitchation, does not represent the velocity of flow but the chemical equilibrium. As flowstone occurs quite frequently a special symbol needed to be found. The small parallel dashes did a good job as they also showed the ground structure. Unfortunately several surveyors characterised clay by a series of small dashes, which can lead to some confusion.§Mit Ausnahme von Erde (Humus) besteht diese Klasse aus Sedimenten, deren Korngrösse und daraus folgend deren Namen von der Fliessgeschwindigkeit der sie befördernden Gewässer abhängen. In fliessendem Wasser wird Sand abgelagert, in stehendem Wasser Lehm. Im Gegensatz dazu ist Sinter (siehe dort), welcher durch chemische Ausfällung von gesättigten Wässern entsteht, nicht von der Fliessgeschwindigkeit, sondern vom Sättigungsgrad des Wassers abhängig. Da Sinter häufig vorkommt, gibt es ein eigenes Symbol dafür. Die kleinen parallelen Striche sind gut geeignet, da sie auch die Bodenstruktur wiedergeben können. Leider haben einige Zeichner das Symbol, das wir für Sinter vorschlagen, für Lehm verwendet, was zu Verwirrungen führen kann.§A l'exception de l'humus, ce groupe représente un sédiment dont la granulométrie et donc l'appellation dépend de la vélocité du courant d'eau l'ayant déposé. En eau courante le sable se dépose, alors qu'en eau stagnante c'est l'argile qui se dépose. Par contraste, le concrétionnement, qui provient d'une réaction chimique, ne représente pas une vitesse d'écoulement, mais un équilibre chimique. Comme le concrétionnement au sol est observé de façon courante, un symbole spécial devait etre trouvé. Les petits traits parallcles utilisés pour représenter les concrétions au sol jusqu'alors ont toujours été trcs utiles, puisque cela permet de montrer la structure du sol.§Con l'eccezione dell'humus, questa categoria raggruppa sedimenti la cui dimensione, e quindi la denominazione, c legata alla velocitr della corrente dell'acqua che li ha deposti. Cin li differenzia dalla "colata di concrezione" (vedi), che c un fenomeno chimico e non fisico. Si c percin deciso di riunire in un simbolo unico tutti i sedimenti fini, indipendentemente dalla loro classificazione. Tale simbolo corrisponde a quello precedentemente usato per rappresentare la sola sabbia. In questo modo c rimasto a disposizione il simbolo precedentemente utilizzato per rappresentare l'argilla o il limo (serie di trattini orizzontali), che viene ora impiegato per la colata di concrezione.§V tej skupini so z izjemo zemlje sedimenti, pri katerih je velikost delcev in tudi ime odvisna od hitrosti prenasujoce vode. V tekoci vodi se odlaga pesek, v stojeci pa mulj oz. glina. S tem se locijo od sige, ki je rezultat kemicnih procesov. Pod en znak smo se odlocili zdruziti vse fine sedimente, ne glede na njihovo klasifikacijo. Zaradi tega je ostal prost znak, ki se je prej uporabljal za glino, to so kratke vzporedne crtice. Ta znak se zdaj uporablja za oznacevanje sige, ki seveda potrebuje lasten razpoznaven znak. §Svi u ovoj grupi, s iznimkom humusa, spadaju u sedimente cija velicina zrna, a prema tome i ime, ovisi o brzini struje vode koja ih nosi. U tekucoj vodi pijesak se talozi, gdje se u stojecoj vodi talozi glina. Tako se razdvajaju od sigovine koje je posljedica kemijskog procesa. Zato su svi fini sedimenti zdruzeni pd jednim znakom bez obzira na njihovu klasifikaciju.§With the exception of humus this group is a sediment whose grain size and therefore names depend on the velocity of current of the carrying water. In flowing water sand is deposited whereas in standing water clay is deposited. In contrast to this the flowstone (see there), which is a chemical precipitchation, does not represent the velocity of flow but the chemical equilibrium. As flowstone occurs quite frequently a special symbol needed to be found. The small parallel dashes did a good job as they also showed the ground structure. Unfortunately several surveyors characterised clay by a series of small dashes, which can lead to some confusion.§Met uitzondering van Humus, bestaat deze groep uit sedimenten waarvan de korrelgrootte en de namen afhangen van de stroomsnelheid van het vervoerende water. In stromend water wordt zand afgezet, klei wordt in stilstaand water afgezet. Druipsteen daarin tegen (zie daar) is een chemische neerslag en geeft niet de stroomsnelheid weer, maar het chemisch evenwicht. Als druipsteen veel voorkomt dan is een speciaal symbool nodig. De kleine parallelle streepjes werken goed ze kunnen tegelijk de bodemstructuur laten zien. Ongelukkigerwijs hebben verscheidende grotmeters klei afgebeeld met kleine streepjes wat kan leiden tot verwarring.§§§clay_covered_wall§0§Clay-Covered Walls§Lehmüberzogene Wände§Parois couvertes d'argile§Pareti ricoperte di argilla§Z glino prekrite stene§Glinom prekrivene stijene§Pereti acoperiti cu argila§Klei-bedekte wanden§§§This symbol can be used to show flooded zones. To show a mud coating, one thin dotted line is drawn behind the cave walls.§Dieses Symbol kann dazu verwendet werden, Stauzonen zu kennzeichnen. Um Schlammüberzüge zu zeigen, sollte eine dünne gepunktete Linie hinter den Höhlenwänden gezeichnet werden.§Ce symbole peut aussi etre utilisé pour montrer les zones temporairement noyées. Pour indiquer une couche continue d'argile, on dessine une ligne pointillée fine derricre la paroi de la cavité.§Questo simbolo pun essere usato anche per evidenziare zone di permanenza di livelli idrici. Per mostrare la ricopertura di argilla, una sottile linea punteggiata viene disegnata al di fuori delle pareti della cavitr§Ta znak se lahko uporabi tudi za prikaz obcasno zalitih delov jame. Za prikaz prekritosti z blatom se narise tanka pikcasta crtica na zunanji strani jamskih sten.§Ovaj simbol moze se rabiti i pri prikazu poplavljenih dijelova. Da se prikaze blatna stijena, tanka tockasta linija nacrtana je iza stijene spilje.§This symbol can be used to show flooded zones. To show a mud coating, one thin dotted line is drawn behind the cave walls.§Dit symbool kan worden gebruikt voor onderwaterzones. Om de modder bedekking te laten zien, teken dan dunne stippen achter de grotwanden.§§§guano§0§Guano§Guano§Guano§Guano§guano§Guano§Guano§Guano§§§as before§wie zuvor§Comme auparavant.§invariato§Kot do zdaj.§Kao i do sada.§as before§Spreekt voor zich.§§§camp§0§Camp§Biwak§Camp§Campo, Bivacco§bivak§Bivak§Tabara§Kamp/Bivak§§§as before§wie zuvor§Comme auparavant.§invariato§Kot do zdaj§Kao i do sada.§as before§Spreekt voor zich.§§§height_of_a_room§1§Height of a Room§Raumhöhe§Hauteur d'une galerie / salle§Altezza di un ambiente§Visina prostora§Visina galerije§Înaltime (alerie-sala)§Hoogte van een zaal§§§An indication on height can be useful for a caver who doesn´t draw longitudinal sections. But since this is highly recommended (see documentation of the 9. National Nongress 991, Charmey) this symbol is not going to be used very often.§Eine Abschätzung der Raumhöhe kann wichtig sein für Pläne, zu denen es keine Längsschnitte gibt. Da das Zeichnen von Längsschnitten jedoch dringend angeraten wird (vergl. Dokumentation 9. Nationaler Kongress 1991, Charmey) wird dieses Symbol ohnehin nicht allzu häufig verwendet werden.§Une indication de hauteur peut etre utile lorsque le topographe ne représente pas de coupe de la cavité. Mais comme une représentation en coupe est fortement recommandée (voir la documentation du 9. Congrcs National en 1991 r Charmey), ce symbole ne devrait pas etre utilisé souvent.§L'indicazione dell'altezza di un ambiente ipogeo pun essere utile nel caso in cui non venga disegnata la Sezione longitudinale. Dal momento che si raccomanda calorosamente di disegnarla (vedi Dériaz, 1991), questo simbolo, mantenuto per consistenza, dovrebbe essere usato molto raramente. La misura c espressa in metri.§Podatek o visini prostora je zelo uporaben pri jamarjih, ki ne risejo profila jame. Od kar pa je profil jame med visoko priporocenimi deli nacrta ( glej dokumentacijo 9. Nacionalnega kongresa 1991, Charmey), ta podatek ni vec tako uporaben.§Indikator visine je koristan za spiljare koji ne crtaju profil speleoloskog objekta. Otkad je profil krajnje preporucljiv (dokumentacija 9. Nacionalnog Kongresa 1991, Charmey), simbol se ne koristiti cesto.§An indication on height can be useful for a caver who doesn´t draw longitudinal sections. But since this is highly recommended (see documentation of the 9. National Nongress 991, Charmey) this symbol is not going to be used very often.§Een indicatie van de hoogte kan bruikbaar zijn voor een speleoloog die geen dwarsdoorsnedes tekent. Maar dit wordt afgeraden (zie documentatie van het negende Nationale Congres 991, Charmey) zal dit symbool niet veel meer gebruikt worden.§§§anastomosen_karren§0§Anostomosen - Karren§Anostomosen - Karren§Anastomoses - Lapiez§Anastomosi - Karren§Anastomoza - skraplje§Anastomoza - Skrape§Anastomoze - lapiezuri§Vlechtende micro-gangetjes - Karren§§§as before§wie zuvor§Comme auparavant.§invariato§Kot do zdaj§Kao i do sada.§as before§Spreekt voor zich.§§§cauliflower_disc§0§Cauliflower-Calcite / Disk§Blumenkohlsinter / Disk§Concrétionnement en choux-fleurs - Disques§Cavolfiori - Dischi di concrezione§Karfjolce - kapniske plosce§Karfioli - Nakapne ploce§Clusterite-Coralite - discuri§Kalk-bloemkool - Disk§§§These two symbols for calcite are of a regional importance and can be quite useful.§Diese beiden Symbole sind v.a. von regionaler Bedeutung, können aber ganz brauchbar sein.§Ces deux symboles ont une importance régionale et peuvent etre utiles.§Questi due simboli per forme particolari di concrezionamento hanno importanza locale e possono essere piuttosto utili.§Obe oznaki  manjsih kapniskih oblik sta lokalne pomembnosti in znata biti zelo uporabni.§Ova dva simbola za kalcitne ukrase su regionalnog znacaja i mogu biti prilicno korisni.§These two symbols for calcite are of a regional importance and can be quite useful.§Deze twee symbolen voor Calciet zijn regionaal belangrijk en kunnen handig zijn.§§§bones§0§Bones§Knochen§Ossements§Ossa§kosti§Kosti§Oase§Botten§§§This symbol does not need any further explanation.§Dieses Symbol braucht keine weitere Erklärung.§Pas besoin de longues explications pour ce symbole ...§Questo simbolo non richiede ulteriori spiegazioni.§Ta znak ne potrebuje dodatnih razlag.§Simbol ne trazi objasnjenje.§This symbol does not need any further explanation.§Dit symbool behoeft geen verdere verklaring§§§human_activity§0§Human Activity§Menschliche Artefakte§Traces d'activité humaine§Modificazioni umane§Clovekove spremembe oz. ostanki§Ljudska aktivnost§Urme de activitate antropica§Menselijke activiteit§§§This symbol is used for man-made changements and/or relicts in caves, including e.g. artwork / drawing / pottery / old mining sites / human bones. Preferably, it will be used for historic/prehistoric changements!§Dieses Symbol zeigt von Menschen hervorgerufene Veränderungen in Höhlen wie z.B. Höhlenzeichnungen, menschliche Knochen, Töpfereien. Es wird v.a. für historische / prähistorische menschliche Veränderungen verwendet werden.§Ce symbole est utilisé pour indiquer les restes ou modifications apportées par l'homme dans une cavité. Par exemple : oeuvre d'art, dessin, poterie, ancienne mine, ossements humains. A utiliser de préférence pour des activités historiques ou prehistoriques!§Questo simbolo viene utilizzato per modifiche di origine umana e/o reperti, ivi compresi dipinti, graffiti, vasellame, antichi siti minerari, ossa umane. Preferibilmente dovrebbe essere utilizzato per modifiche preistoriche o di etr antica.§Ta znak se uporablja za clovekove posege in ostanke v jamskem okolju. Tako jamske slikarije, loncevino, ostanke rudnikov kot cloveske kosti. Predvsem naj bi se uporabljal za zgodovinske/ prazgodovinske ostanke.§Ovaj simbol se koristi za ljudski napravljene promjene i/ili artifakte u spiljama (kao crtezi, grincarija, ostaci rudnika, ljudske kosti). Prvenstveno se koristi za povjesne ili prehistorijske izmjene (ostatke).§This symbol is used for man-made changements and/or relicts in caves, including e.g. artwork / drawing / pottery / old mining sites / human bones. Preferably, it will be used for historic/prehistoric changements!§Dit symbool wordt gebruikt voor menselijke veranderingen en/of relikwieën in grotten inclusief bijvoorbeeld kunst / tekeningen / aardewerk / oude groeves / menselijke botten. Bij voorkeur worden deze gebruikt voor historische/pre-historische veranderingen§§§